<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Academic publications</title><link href="https://fhcflx.github.io/alt-pub/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://fhcflx.github.io/alt-pub/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://fhcflx.github.io/alt-pub/</id><updated>2017-12-27T16:03:45-03:00</updated><entry><title>Complete guide to contributing to Academic Publications</title><link href="https://fhcflx.github.io/alt-pub/complete-guide-to-contributing-to-academic-publications.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-12-27T16:03:45-03:00</published><updated>2017-12-27T16:03:45-03:00</updated><author><name>Francisco H C Felix</name></author><id>tag:fhcflx.github.io,2017-12-27:/alt-pub/complete-guide-to-contributing-to-academic-publications.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/fhcflx/alt-pub/releases?colorB=dd4814"&gt;&lt;img alt="GitHub release" src="https://img.shields.io/github/release/fhcflx/alt-pub.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.845747"&gt;&lt;img alt="Project DOI" src="https://zenodo.org/badge/DOI/10.5281/zenodo.845747.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.5435968"&gt;&lt;img alt="Article DOI" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/ARTICLE--DOI-10.6084/m9..5435968-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=""&gt;&lt;img alt="pdf" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/pdf-download-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This guide will walk you through the steps to contribute in an ethical and free manner to the Academic Publications page, and actively participate in the &lt;a href="https://www.fosteropenscience.eu/content/what-open-science-introduction"&gt;Open Science&lt;/a&gt;  movement [1]. Any issues may be addressed to the project&amp;rsquo;s author e-mail (&lt;a href="mailto:valkyr.ie@outlook.com"&gt;fhcflx@outlook.com&lt;/a&gt;) or to his Twitter &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/fhcflx"&gt;@fhcflx&lt;/a&gt;. The …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/fhcflx/alt-pub/releases?colorB=dd4814"&gt;&lt;img alt="GitHub release" src="https://img.shields.io/github/release/fhcflx/alt-pub.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.845747"&gt;&lt;img alt="Project DOI" src="https://zenodo.org/badge/DOI/10.5281/zenodo.845747.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.5435968"&gt;&lt;img alt="Article DOI" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/ARTICLE--DOI-10.6084/m9..5435968-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=""&gt;&lt;img alt="pdf" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/pdf-download-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This guide will walk you through the steps to contribute in an ethical and free manner to the Academic Publications page, and actively participate in the &lt;a href="https://www.fosteropenscience.eu/content/what-open-science-introduction"&gt;Open Science&lt;/a&gt;  movement [1]. Any issues may be addressed to the project&amp;rsquo;s author e-mail (&lt;a href="mailto:valkyr.ie@outlook.com"&gt;fhcflx@outlook.com&lt;/a&gt;) or to his Twitter &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/fhcflx"&gt;@fhcflx&lt;/a&gt;. The project is free to be copied, modified and hacked. Comments and contributions are most welcome! Science must be made by all people and freely benefit all people!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-contribute-to-academic-publications"&gt;Why Contribute to Academic Publications?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are more and more ways of publishing all types of academic and non-academic material. Preprints, postprints, self-archiving, conference poster and slides and other resources presented at meetings, congresses, etc. Raw data from research, experimental design, projects for funding agencies or review boards, monographs, reviews, comments, peer reviews. The diversity of materials that can be published in some form in electronic format will only be limited by human imagination. In the future, this promises to be the source of a major revolution in scientific research and will give rise to new fields of study, such as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meta-research"&gt;scientific meta-research&lt;/a&gt; [2], research about the research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, why another electronic publishing medium? Besides, this medium has no features that other channels strive to possess, such as peer review, indexing, automatic &lt;a href="https://doi.org"&gt;DOI&lt;/a&gt; number assignment, and more. The truth is that this project constitutes only one among many. In this way, I do not really see weakness, because the future volume of data produced by humanity will be so great that there will always be room for practically all initiatives. However, I have identified some gaps in the most popular projects these days, in which I would like to innovate, making Academic Publications really the only one of its kind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This is a community-driven and decentralized project.&lt;/strong&gt; Although having a single repository (currently), and having only one administrator (for now), this project can accept an unlimited number of contributions and participants.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This is a completely hackable project.&lt;/strong&gt; Just need to have an account on the remote &lt;a href="https://git-scm.com"&gt;Git&lt;/a&gt; server we use now (&lt;a href="https://github.com"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, but it may not be the one used in the future, nor the only one) and contribute. You can change just about everything. The more the community contributions increase, the more the project will change and be shaped in a manner of its own. The power of &lt;a href="https://git-scm.com"&gt;Git&lt;/a&gt; local versioning management will allow the community to easily use any remote server it wants, even several of them at the same time in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This is a secure project.&lt;/strong&gt; Using &lt;a href="https://www.gnupg.org/gph/en/manual/c14.html"&gt;GPG keys signatures&lt;/a&gt;, authors can rest assured of protecting their authority and precedence over their work. The project is based on the idea of ​​free access, but with attribution of authorship. Thus, it is completely plagiarism-proof (plagiarism can occur, but with &lt;a href="https://www.gnupg.org/gph/en/manual/c14.html"&gt;GPG keys signatures&lt;/a&gt; it will be possible to immediately prove authorship).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This is a fully citable and traceable project.&lt;/strong&gt; Using existing electronic archiving platforms (&lt;a href="https://figshare.com"&gt;figshare&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://zenodo.org"&gt;Zenodo&lt;/a&gt;), a &lt;a href="https://doi.org"&gt;DOI&lt;/a&gt; number can be assigned to the project as a whole and to each publication in particular. For example, this text is registered in &lt;a href="https://figshare.com"&gt;figshare&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href="https://doi.org"&gt;DOI&lt;/a&gt; 10.6084/m9.figshare.5735136 and the complete project (current version of Academic Publications) is registered in &lt;a href="https://zenodo.org"&gt;Zenodo&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href="https://doi.org"&gt;DOI&lt;/a&gt; 10.5281/zenodo.594582. There are ways to automate this process, but to perform a minimum quality check, the ideal is to keep the process through curatorship.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This is a project with community-verified quality.&lt;/strong&gt; Instead of an editor(s) as usual publishing channels, this project will have a curator(s), who will look after the minimum quality standards and organization of the contributed material. Over time, the community will actively critique and review posts by commenting, opening &lt;a href="https://guides.github.com/features/issues/"&gt;issues&lt;/a&gt; and making &lt;a href="https://help.github.com/articles/creating-a-pull-request-from-a-fork/"&gt;pull requests&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This is a cool project!&lt;/strong&gt; I strongly believe in community participation in science communication projects and integration of scientific knowledge. Creating this project and being part of it, even if it does not get a great resonance, is already a great privilege! It&amp;rsquo;s one of the coolest things I&amp;rsquo;ve ever done!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="contribution-formats"&gt;Contribution formats:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is not a scientific journal, has no ISSN number registration, nor is it indexed in any academic database. There are simple ways to index work on Google Scholar, which we describe elsewhere. Thus, it is not correct to refer to the material posted here as having been &amp;ldquo;published&amp;rdquo;, nor register this information in curricula. While personally advocating a less restrictive view of &lt;em&gt;publishing&lt;/em&gt; (hence the title of the project), this distinction is necessary to avoid abuse. It should be made clear that a &amp;ldquo;publication&amp;rdquo; (if you want to call it that way) in this project is not a &amp;ldquo;peer-reviewed publication in an indexed journal&amp;rdquo;. More appropriately, the contribution of unpublished material is to be called as &lt;em&gt;preprint&lt;/em&gt; and of previously published material as &lt;em&gt;postprint&lt;/em&gt;. These are the two basic modalities of &lt;em&gt;contributing&lt;/em&gt; supported by this project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, this is a non-exhaustive list of formats that can be submitted:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preprint:&lt;/strong&gt; academic material written for the purpose of publication in a traditional journal or other publication channel, deposited &lt;strong&gt;before&lt;/strong&gt; submission and peer review . More recently, a number of preprints never get published in peer-reviewed channels, retaining their pre-publishing status, and even being quoted as preprints. A precondition for depositing &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Preprint"&gt;preprints&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is to check if the vehicle where the final publication is desired allows this practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same formats that can be published in a conventional channel can be deposited as preprints:
  - &lt;strong&gt;articles&lt;/strong&gt;
  - &lt;strong&gt;reviews&lt;/strong&gt;
  - &lt;strong&gt;commentaries&lt;/strong&gt; (letters) and other forms of &lt;em&gt;front matter&lt;/em&gt;
  - &lt;strong&gt;brief communications&lt;/strong&gt;, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Postprint:&lt;/strong&gt; less common practice until the emergence of channels such as Researchgate, &lt;a href="https://figshare.com"&gt;figshare&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://zenodo.org"&gt;Zenodo&lt;/a&gt; and others. It is the deposit of material &lt;strong&gt;after&lt;/strong&gt; submission, peer review and publication in traditional channels. A prerequisite for this modality is the ownership of authorship rights over the work by the authors. Some traditional journals allow for the deposit in institutional repositories.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with preprints, the same formats can be deposited as [postprints][postprint].
3. &lt;strong&gt;Self-archiving:&lt;/strong&gt; an arbitrary distinction in relation to the modalities described above. It can be said that both the pre and postprints deposited by the author are forms of self-archiving. In this way, it becomes less relevant to distinguish this modality. It could be said, more specifically, that texts created exclusively for self-archiving - or no longer intended for publication (eg material submitted but not accepted in some publication channel) could fall under this definition. However, a less strict definition of &lt;em&gt;preprint&lt;/em&gt; also encompasses these assumptions. Institutional depositing of &lt;em&gt;postprint&lt;/em&gt; material can also be refered this way.
4. &lt;strong&gt;Research material:&lt;/strong&gt; experimental designs, research projects, raw data, statistical analysis, research notebooks, and any other materials, texts, figures, collections of data that may be deposited in a &lt;strong&gt;free and accessible&lt;/strong&gt; form, under a license compatible with [Open Science][os] (in most cases, &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0&lt;/a&gt;). Any posted material will automatically be publicly available. That said, it is a great way to show the community the progress of a research line.
5. &lt;strong&gt;Conference presentation:&lt;/strong&gt; posters, slides, abstracts, extended abstracts, complete articles published in conference proceedings. Once again, only material whose authors own the copyright may be posted.
6. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grey_literature"&gt;Grey literature&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; according to the Prague definition, &amp;ldquo;that which is produced on all levels of government, academics, business and industry in print and electronic formats, but which is not controlled by commercial publishers, i.e., where publishing is not the primary activity of the producing body&amp;rdquo; [3]. Most of the time, internal publications and alternative formats in public or business institutions. In the less restricted definition of Farace &amp;amp; Schöpfel [3], it includes white papers, blog posts, technical manuals, and many other non-traditional forms of academic material. The authors&amp;rsquo; copyright control requirement also applies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="instructions-for-authors"&gt;Instructions for Authors:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only academic material will be accepted. No advertising or commercial material may be included. If the authors intend to use some or all of the material to be contributed in a commercial venture in the future, it is recommended that the contribution not be made. For all formats, authors must submit their full name and affiliation. In addition, they are asked to write three or four lines (around 200 to 400 characters) to show on the main page as a summary of the post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="limits-for-contributed-material"&gt;Limits for contributed material:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preprint:&lt;/strong&gt; There are no limits on number of characters or requirements for posting. All texts will be converted using the program &lt;a href="https://pandoc.org"&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href="https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/syntax"&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; format and later parsed into files in &lt;code&gt;pdf&lt;/code&gt; format. The final aspect is standardized and an example of the typography used can be seen here. Texts in draft format, revision format or final submission format for another publication medium may be accepted. Audio-visual material (figures, graphics, videos, sound) can be received in any format (individual files), but there is no guarantee that they can always be included in the final result, depending on the limitations of the infrastructure used (see next subsection). Authors should first check whether the media to which they wish to submit their papers at a later stage is compatible with preprint (see next section). At this time, it is only possible to receive submissions in Portuguese and English and in the formats supported by the &lt;a href="https://pandoc.org"&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt; program (see next subsection).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Postprint:&lt;/strong&gt; The same as for preprints applies here. The difference is that authors should keep full copyright on their works. If you have signed a copyright transfer term to another medium, this is no longer possible. Some journals and publishing media allow for self-archiving of &lt;em&gt;drafts&lt;/em&gt; by the author (next section).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Self-archiving:&lt;/strong&gt; the same limitations of text and audiovisual resources. The authors should state that, at least at the moment, they do not intend to publish the material. However, no obligation is required (authors are free to change their mind in the future and publish their material, in which case &lt;em&gt;self-archiving&lt;/em&gt; is a form of &lt;em&gt;preprint&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research material:&lt;/strong&gt; in addition to text and audiovisual material, it may include spreadsheets and databases. Supported formats are listed in the next subsection. Authors should attach an &amp;ldquo;abstract&amp;rdquo; or explanatory text, arbitrarily concise, provided enough to explain what the shared dataset is about. &lt;em&gt;No information concerning human experimentation will be accepted if any participant may be identified directly or indirectly&lt;/em&gt; (see subsection on &lt;em&gt;desidentification&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conference presentation:&lt;/strong&gt; The best way to post posters and slides is to deposit them into a specialized service such as &lt;a href="https://www.slideshare.net"&gt;Slideshare&lt;/a&gt; and include them on the post page. If the authors do not want this solution, you can include a link to download the presentation file. Authors should attach an &amp;ldquo;abstract&amp;rdquo; or explanatory text, arbitrarily concise, provided enough to explain what the presentation is about. They should also indicate in which event (full name, place and date) the presentation occurred. The contribution of abstracts, extended abstracts and complete articles published in proceedings goes in the same way as the postprint of peer-reviewed material.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grey literature:&lt;/strong&gt; In general, the same limits of format, content and ethical restrictions apply to this type of material.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="formats-accepted"&gt;Formats accepted:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Text:&lt;/strong&gt; plain text (&lt;code&gt;.txt&lt;/code&gt;), microsoft office (&lt;code&gt;.doc, .docx, .rtf&lt;/code&gt;), open office (&lt;code&gt;.odt, .fodt&lt;/code&gt;), &lt;a href="https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/syntax"&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; (many &amp;ldquo;flavors&amp;rdquo;) , html, LaTeX, reStructuredText.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Images:&lt;/strong&gt; any format, but only the &lt;code&gt;jpg, png&lt;/code&gt; and&lt;code&gt;gif&lt;/code&gt; formats can be viewed on the page. Others can be converted or attached as links to download the files. It is possible that very large images or some formats may not be supported by the &lt;a href="https://pages.github.com"&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt; infrastructure where the page is hosted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Graphics:&lt;/strong&gt; R and LaTeX codes will be accepted to be converted into images with rmarkdown.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video:&lt;/strong&gt; the preferred way to contribute videos is to upload them to &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com"&gt;Youtube&lt;/a&gt; or similar services and then embbed it in the page.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Audio:&lt;/strong&gt; any format, but files will only be available for download. Size limits may apply.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sheets:&lt;/strong&gt; any format, but only the &lt;code&gt;csv&lt;/code&gt; format can be viewed on the page. Others can be converted or attached as links to download the files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Databases:&lt;/strong&gt; any format, but files will only be available for download. Size limits may apply.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="ethical-disclosure"&gt;Ethical disclosure:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="preprint-compliance"&gt;Preprint compliance:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Authors who contribute with preprints should check that the vehicle for which the final submission is intended complies with this practice. On the &lt;a href="http://www.sherpa.ac.uk/romeo/index.php?la=pt&amp;amp;fIDnum=|&amp;amp;mode=simple"&gt;SHERPA/RoMEO&lt;/a&gt; project page one can easily search for the name or ISSN of journals. Vehicles listed as &amp;ldquo;green&amp;rdquo; allow pre- and postprint. As a rule of thumb, any work published on Open Access vehicles with a &lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/?lang=pt_BR"&gt;Creative Commons&lt;/a&gt; license can be auto-archived. If there are any questions, the author of this project can help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="ethics-for-the-use-of-experimental-animals"&gt;Ethics for the use of experimental animals:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the contribution of self-archiving or research materials using experimental animals, the &lt;strong&gt;project acceptance letter&lt;/strong&gt; by a &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.apa.org/science/leadership/care/guidelines.aspx"&gt;Committee on Animal Research and Ethics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; must be submitted with the contribution. Postprints, once they have already passed through editorial and peer reviews, are exempt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="ethics-for-human-experimentation"&gt;Ethics for human experimentation:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the contribution of self-archiving or research materials on human experimentation, the &lt;strong&gt;acceptance letter&lt;/strong&gt; of the project by an &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.fda.gov/RegulatoryInformation/Guidances/ucm126420.htm"&gt;Institutional Review Board&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, in addition to the &lt;strong&gt;informed consent form&lt;/strong&gt; signed by each participant (or legal representative) must be sent together with the contribution. Postprints, once they have already passed through editorial and peer reviews, are exempt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, materials that have not been properly desidentified will not be accepted. This process aims to avoid the direct or indirect identification of the experimental subjects in a clinical study. Typically, simply remove the following items from the results, databases, or text:
- Name, including initials or surnames.
- Provenance, even the city. If necessary to identify patients from more than one treatment center, code the information (eg &amp;ldquo;center A&amp;rdquo;).
- Date of diagnosis, date of last information collected, date of birth, other dates.
- Other information that, in combination, may identify the research subjects.
Likewise, in the contribution of audiovisual material from clinical studies, those that allow person identification will not be accepted. For example: photos of the whole face can not be accepted, only of parts of the face, discharacterizing the identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="attribution-of-doi"&gt;Attribution of &lt;a href="https://doi.org"&gt;DOI&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order for the post to have a &lt;a href="https://doi.org"&gt;DOI&lt;/a&gt; number assigned, you will need to deposit the files in &lt;a href="https://figshare.com"&gt;figshare&lt;/a&gt;, or another compatible service. The authors themselves can do this, or they must clearly state in the contributed material an &lt;em&gt;authorization&lt;/em&gt; so that the author of this project can deposit it on their behalf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="submission-of-contribution"&gt;Submission of contribution:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="using-git-and-github"&gt;Using Git and GitHub:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you already have an account in &lt;a href="https://github.com"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; and you already know how to use &lt;a href="https://git-scm.com"&gt;Git&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;fork&lt;/em&gt; and clone the project, add your &lt;a href="https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/syntax"&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; files in the  &lt;code&gt;content / posts&lt;/code&gt; folder (in Portuguese and/or English), add figures in &lt;code&gt;content / images&lt;/code&gt;, add pdf in&lt;code&gt;content / docs&lt;/code&gt; and make a &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://help.github.com/articles/creating-a-pull-request-from-a-fork/"&gt;pull request&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you do not know any of this yet but would like to learn, &lt;a href="https://try.github.io/levels/1/challenges/1"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.atlassian.com/git/tutorials"&gt;Atlassian&lt;/a&gt; have great tutorials!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enjoy and hack the project! Make changes, introduce new features and functionalities, be part of the project!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="using-the-good-old-e-mail"&gt;Using the good old e-mail:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not interested in Git? No problem, send an email with your files attached, in the accepted formats.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even simpler, are you contributing with simple text? Just write your full text in the body of the email and send it! Follow the instructions for the authors and contribute!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="commenting-on-other-contributions"&gt;Commenting on other contributions:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Through GitHub: open an &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://guides.github.com/features/issues/"&gt;issue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the project page, leave your comments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="references"&gt;References:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open science, open questions / Sarita Albagli, Maria Lucia Maciel &amp;amp; Alexandre Hannud Abdo organizers. – Brasília: IBICT; Rio de Janeiro: UNIRIO, 2015. 312 p.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ioannidis, John P. A.; Fanelli, Daniele; Dunne, Debbie Drake; Goodman, Steven N. (2015). Meta-research: Evaluation and Improvement of Research Methods and Practices. PLOS Biology. 13 (10): e1002264.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grey literature in library and information studies / edited by Dominic J. Farace and Joachim Schöpfel, 2010, Walter de Gruyter GmbH &amp;amp; Co. KG, Berlin/New York, ISBN 978-3-598-11793-0.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="guide"></category></entry><entry><title>Management of infantile hemangiomas</title><link href="https://fhcflx.github.io/alt-pub/management-of-infantile-hemangiomas.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-07-28T16:03:45-03:00</published><updated>2017-07-28T16:03:45-03:00</updated><author><name>Francisco H C Felix</name></author><id>tag:fhcflx.github.io,2017-07-28:/alt-pub/management-of-infantile-hemangiomas.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/fhcflx/alt-pub/releases?colorB=dd4814"&gt;&lt;img alt="GitHub release" src="https://img.shields.io/github/release/fhcflx/alt-pub.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.594582"&gt;&lt;img alt="Project DOI" src="https://zenodo.org/badge/DOI/10.5281/zenodo.594582.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1110958.1"&gt;&lt;img alt="Article DOI" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/ARTICLE--DOI-10.7490/f1000research.1110958.1-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://f1000research.com/slides/4-1231#"&gt;&lt;img alt="pdf" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/pdf-download-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This lecture was an invited presentation at XIX Brazilian Congress of Cancerology (CONCAN), in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hemangiomas are common pediatric tumors often described as birthmarks, more frequent in infants and at the head and neck region. Most of them regress spontaneously without any sequelae. A third of all infantile hemangiomas will …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/fhcflx/alt-pub/releases?colorB=dd4814"&gt;&lt;img alt="GitHub release" src="https://img.shields.io/github/release/fhcflx/alt-pub.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.594582"&gt;&lt;img alt="Project DOI" src="https://zenodo.org/badge/DOI/10.5281/zenodo.594582.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1110958.1"&gt;&lt;img alt="Article DOI" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/ARTICLE--DOI-10.7490/f1000research.1110958.1-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://f1000research.com/slides/4-1231#"&gt;&lt;img alt="pdf" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/pdf-download-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This lecture was an invited presentation at XIX Brazilian Congress of Cancerology (CONCAN), in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hemangiomas are common pediatric tumors often described as birthmarks, more frequent in infants and at the head and neck region. Most of them regress spontaneously without any sequelae. A third of all infantile hemangiomas will be problematic, presenting with complications due to their size and/or topography or leaving sequelae (fibrofatty masses, discoloration, laxity, telangiectasia or scarring due to ulceration). The treatment of problematic infantile hemangiomas at Brazil was recently regulated by an administrative rule from the Ministry of Health (number 849, December 5th, 2011). The first choice was deemed to be oral prednisone. The other choices are interferon and beta-blockers. Surgery is indicated in selected cases. Non-problematic cases should be followed carefully without any treatment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this lecture, I have made a brief review of the evidence behind these treatment choices. I used primarily the Oxford Centre for Evidence Based Medicine 2011 levels of evidence, ranging from A (best quality evidence available) to D (only limited evidence available, or no evidence). I reviewed therapeutic studies and extracted information about efficacy and safety profiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have found two major studies using prednisone/prednisolone. Bennet et al (2001) published a rigorous systematic review of observational studies, however there was confounding in the dose-response relation evaluation. Pandey et al (2009) published an observational study with 2013 patients, but the case definition, response evaluation and treatment duration were unclear. Both reported efficacy around 80-90%. Once there were no high quality evidence from randomized, double-blind trials, I gave prednisone/prednisolone a C level grade for efficacy, and a D level grade for safety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have found very limited evidence for the use of interferon, mostly from small number of cases observational reports. Thus, I gave it a D level grade. Due to the ocurrence of serious neurologic complications in patients that used interferon for hemangiomas, this treatment is currently widely contraindicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For propranolol, the main beta-blocker used to treat problematic infantile hemangiomas, I have found a myriad observational reports, ranging from a few to many hundreds of cases described. Additionally, Hogeling et al (2011) have published the first randomized, double-blind clinical trial comparing propranolol to placebo. It was a small sized, phase I-II equivalent clinical trial. Nonetheless, it reported clear evidence of efficacy and acceptable safety of propranolol treatment for infantile hemangioma; Because of this study, I gave propranolol treatment a C &amp;ldquo;plus&amp;rdquo; level grade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: this lecture was presented in 2012. Since then, other high quality level trials reported their results, and my updated grade, as for 2015, would be certainly B.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been treating pediatric patients with problematic infantile hemangiomas with off-label propranolol since 2009. I published a small report with observational retrospective evaluation of results in Treatment of children and adolescents with hemangioma using propranolol: preliminary results from a retrospective study. JC Albuquerque, RA Magalhaes, JA Felix, MVR Bastos (…) - Sao Paulo Medical Journal, 2014 – doi:10.1590/1516-3180.2014.1321575  (this report was referred in this lecture as &amp;lsquo;submitted to publication&amp;rsquo; and awaiting approval).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src="//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/key/xCfuvwFzyugOAa" width="595" height="485" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;" allowfullscreen&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;div style="margin-bottom:5px"&gt; &lt;strong&gt; &lt;a href="//www.slideshare.net/FranciscoFelix6/concan-2012-aula" title="Abordagem atual dos hemangiomas" target="_blank"&gt;Abordagem atual dos hemangiomas&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/strong&gt; de &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="//www.slideshare.net/FranciscoFelix6" target="_blank"&gt;Francisco H C Felix&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="slides"></category></entry><entry><title>Treatment of infantile hemangiomas</title><link href="https://fhcflx.github.io/alt-pub/treatment-of-infantile-hemangiomas.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-07-10T16:03:45-03:00</published><updated>2017-07-10T16:03:45-03:00</updated><author><name>Francisco H C Felix</name></author><id>tag:fhcflx.github.io,2017-07-10:/alt-pub/treatment-of-infantile-hemangiomas.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/fhcflx/alt-pub/releases?colorB=dd4814"&gt;&lt;img alt="GitHub release" src="https://img.shields.io/github/release/fhcflx/alt-pub.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.594582"&gt;&lt;img alt="Project DOI" src="https://zenodo.org/badge/DOI/10.5281/zenodo.594582.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.2059821"&gt;&lt;img alt="Article DOI" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/ARTICLE--DOI-10.6084/m9.figshare.2059821-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://ndownloader.figshare.com/files/3658257"&gt;&lt;img alt="pdf" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/pdf-download-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Hemangiomas are benign tumors formed by the proliferation of blood vessels and are the most common tumors of childhood. Their evolution is well known. They are tiny or inapparent at birth and increase rapidly in the first months of life (proliferative phase). After a variable time, the lesions stabilize …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/fhcflx/alt-pub/releases?colorB=dd4814"&gt;&lt;img alt="GitHub release" src="https://img.shields.io/github/release/fhcflx/alt-pub.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.594582"&gt;&lt;img alt="Project DOI" src="https://zenodo.org/badge/DOI/10.5281/zenodo.594582.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.2059821"&gt;&lt;img alt="Article DOI" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/ARTICLE--DOI-10.6084/m9.figshare.2059821-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://ndownloader.figshare.com/files/3658257"&gt;&lt;img alt="pdf" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/pdf-download-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Hemangiomas are benign tumors formed by the proliferation of blood vessels and are the most common tumors of childhood. Their evolution is well known. They are tiny or inapparent at birth and increase rapidly in the first months of life (proliferative phase). After a variable time, the lesions stabilize and spontaneous regression occurs, which is complete between 3 and 9 years of life. Large lesions can last through adolescence and leave important scars. About 24% of cases of childhood hemangiomas present complications, and some form of treatment is indicated. The first choice is a systemic corticosteroid, effective in up to 90% of cases, but requiring prolonged treatment at high doses (more than 3 months) and leading to partial response in most patients, with frequent adverse effects. Interferon alpha and vincristine showed effect, albeit slow, in limited series, and can have potential serious side effects. Recently, treatment with propranolol, in usual doses, has shown  excellent short- and medium-term response. As it is a drug with a good safety profile, the authors propose that it be the first choice for the treatment of problematic childhood hemangiomas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="francisco-h-c-felix1"&gt;Francisco H. C. Felix&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pediatric hemato-oncologist, Hospital Infantil Albert Sabin&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Pediatric Onco-hematology Service, Hospital Infantil Albert Sabin (SOHPHIAS)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hemangiomas are tumors formed by the proliferation of blood vessels and are the most common tumors of childhood, affecting about 3-10% of caucasian children. They are more frequent in females (1: 1.4-3.0) in white and non-latino individuals. Its causes are unknown, except for rare genetic syndromes in which its frequency is higher. However, preterm infants (&amp;lt;37 gestational weeks), especially extreme premature infants (&amp;lt;32 weeks) and small gestational age infants (SGA) are at a higher risk of developing hemangiomas. Also maternal age over 30 years and a positive family history, as well as placenta previa and preeclampsia, are associated with increased risk. (Haggstrom, 2007). Histologically, hemangiomas form a heterogeneous group (Table 1) (Marler &amp;amp; Mulliken, 2005), although the most common type is known simply as infantile or capillary hemangioma. In relation to its morphology and presentation, the most commonly used classification in Brazil is Curado (table 2) (Curado, 1992).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evolution of the infantile hemangioma is typical and well known. The lesions are usually minute or inapparent at birth and may increase rapidly in the first months of life (proliferative phase). After a variable time (more commonly until the 3rd month, sometimes until the end of the first year of life), the lesions stabilize. After 1 to 3 years without change, slow spontaneous regression occurs, which is complete between 3 and 9 years of life. Large lesions can last through adolescence and leave important scars. Most cases do not present complications and show spontaneous regression. In 20-40% of the cases residual cicatricial lesions remain. Small hemangiomas (&amp;lt;5 cm in diameter) usually regress completely through age 5 (Adams, 2008).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About 24% of cases of childhood hemangiomas present complications. The most common are ulceration (16%), visual occlusion (5.6%), respiratory obstruction (1.4%), auditory canal obstruction (0.6%), and cardiac involvement (0.4%) (Haggstrom, 2007). Bleeding is uncommon. In general, any complication indicates the need for treatment. In a recently published series, 38% needed treatment. In this series, the majority of the lesions were located on the face (41%) and the most important factor for indication of treatment was the lesion size. Segmental lesions (involving a whole body segment) were much more frequently treated and presented more complications than localized lesions. Despite the treatment, in this series the main delayed complication was the occurrence of disfiguring scars (Haggstrom, 2006).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most appropriate approach for most lesions is watchful waiting, since they are mostly self-limiting and do not determine important sequels or complications. Problematic lesions of large size, rapid growth or risk of sequelae or life threatening should be addressed (Muler &amp;amp; Mulliken, 2005). Pharmacological treatment has few options. The main choices, although widely used, are still based on limited evidence. The first choice is systemic corticosteroids, most often oral prednisone, at high doses (3 to 5 mg/kg/day of prednisone). This was practically the only treatment for which there was some evidence, albeit limited, until 2008. An observational study determined 93% response in children treated for up to 12 weeks at that dose (Sadan, 1996). The only clinical trial compared oral versus intravenous corticosteroids with a small number of patients and subjective assessment of response and no untreated control (Pope, 2007). This trial showed that 65% of the children needed treatment for more than three months. Eventhough these drugs are known to act quickly and have some efficacy in about 90% of cases, a significant amount of the lesions respond only partially. In addition, treatment needs to be prolonged for six months or more, and a significant amount of side effects occur (Pope, 2007). Significant side effects occur in the short to medium term in most patients treated with this dose (Boon, 1999). No studies have evaluated the possible long-term side effects of prolonged exposure to high doses of corticosteroids. However, studies with children treated for leukemia show that there is a significant increase in the incidence of obesity, hypertension and diabetes, even decades after exposure to corticosteroids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Used in about 12% of patients, topical or intralesional corticosteroids, or other types of intralesional treatment have no evidence of efficacy. Surgical resection is only performed in a minority of patients (around 5%) and, since most of the lesions undergo spontaneous regression, it is usually contraindicated. In cases of ulceration, local infection is common and most patients will require local care with topical antibiotics and dressings, although some patients may require systemic antibiotics and hospital admission. Flat hemangiomas are not treated with drugs or surgery, but can be properly conducted with pulsed dye laser, with good aesthetic results. Limited series of patients with large refractory lesions were treated with interferon alpha 2a (Ezekowitz, 1994) or vincristine (Perez, 2002). Although these drugs have shown an effect in the described cases, this effect is slow and partial. In addition, the use of interferon has recently been associated with severe neurological complications (Barlow, 1998).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2008, a communication published in the New England Journal of Medicine reported for the first time the use of propranolol to treat childhood hemangiomas (Léauté-Labrèze, 2008). The first patient was a 4-month-old child with a nasal capillary hemangioma who received high-dose corticosteroids with stabilization of the lesion, but developed hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, possibly due to corticoids. Propranolol at the usual pediatric dose was initiated and an immediate change occurred in the first 24 hours, with change in coloration and &amp;ldquo;softening&amp;rdquo; of the lesion. Ten months later, the lesion was completely flat, regressed. Another 10 patients were treated by the group between 2006 and 2007, with similar results. After this first publication, other reports of cases successfully treated with propranolol were described, and the initial article was already cited about 140 times (a survey conducted in Google Scholar in January 2011).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The subsequent report (Sans, 2009) of the same group that made the discovery showed that propranolol treatment was effective in 100% of the patients they treated, with a rapid, immediate-onset effect that is radiologically evident as early as two months after its inception. They also demonstrated the rapid reversal of complications such as ocular obstruction and ulceration. Due to some cases of recurrence after early termination of treatment, the authors propose that it be done throughout the proliferative phase of the development of hemangiomas, until at least 1 year of age. Another group made similar observations, reporting 87% efficacy in the regression of infantile hemangiomas treated in the proliferative phase (Holmes, 2011). They observed a possible dose-dependent effect and proposed propranolol as the first choice to treat complicated childhood hemangiomas. A large number of case reports followed the first observational study of 2008, showing effect of propranolol in isolated cases of childhood hemangioma in several topographies.
The treatment of pediatric patients with problematic hemangiomas began more than seven years ago when the first patients with an indication of second-choice treatment were referred to receive interferon alpha in the Albert Sabin Infant Oncology Service (SOHP-HIAS). Since January 2009, we have treated patients with hemangiomas with oral propranolol. A research project coordinated by this author was approved by the Institutional Review Board of HIAS in 2009, and is in progress, in data collection phase. It should be added that the use of propranolol for the treatment of infantile hemangiomas is not approved by ANVISA (brazillian regulatory agency) and therefore constitutes an off-label use of this substance. Here at SOHP-HIAS, we report to the Pharmacy and Therapeutics Commission for the non-standard use of propranolol in pediatric patients with hemangiomas. Parents or guardians of children receive detailed explanation of the treatment and it is initiated after informed consent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At present, we indicate treatment with propranolol concomitant with conventional treatment or in children with contraindication to the conventional treatment for infantile hemangiomas. We also treat patients with large residual lesions after conventional therapy or refractory to this therapy. However, we use a reduced dose of corticosteroid (1-2 mg/kg/day) for a short time (1-2 months) in patients who achieve good results in the initial phase of treatment. The dose of propranolol we use is 0.5 to 2.0 mg/kg/day, divided in 1-3 times daily in a stepup fashion. The dose starts at 0.5-1.0 mg/kg/day and we further increase it 50% per week, the target dose reaching 2.0 mg/kg/day in 2-3 weeks. In patients with a slow response or primary refractoriness to propranolol at this dose, we increased the dose (if tolerated) to a maximum of 4.0 mg/kg/day. Treatment with propranolol is maintained up to one year of age or for at least one year in order to avoid relapse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our results are still under evaluation, but apparently we can reproduce the good results already published (Sans, 2009; Holmes, in press). Most patients respond well to treatment, with rapid reduction in hemangioma volume. The first effects (change in color and texture) are noticed in days, while a noticeable reduction can already be identified in 1-2 months. Although this has yet to be proven by adequate studies, our preliminary results indicate that patients can be divided into two groups regarding the speed and intensity of response: a group that responds rapidly and completely, with complete remission within a few months (rapid responders), and a group with a much slower and incomplete response, and may take up to six months to have an objective partial response (slow responders). Some of our patients in the first group responded immediately with low doses and completed treatment with 1.0 mg/kg/day of propranolol, with complete remission. However, in the second group, some patients only responded when the dose was increased to 4.0 mg/kg/day, or when low dose corticosteroid was associated. Possibly, addition of corticoid and/or dose increase may represent ways of reversing partial primary resistance to treatment. In our series, we did not observe cases of secondary resistance. All cases of recurrence after early termination of treatment by the family were adequately treated with re-initiation of propranolol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The incidence of side effects has been low and virtually no patient with hemangioma had to discontinue treatment because of adverse reactions. We contraindicated propranolol therapy for children with heart failure or a history of severe asthma. We received a child whose treatment with propranolol was initiated by another colleague at another health facility who had a severe adverse event episode (severe bronchospasm requiring tracheostomy). For this patient, the dose was started without progressive increase at the maximum level we use. We reiterate the need for close monitoring of the patient in the initial phase of treatment. The American choose to increase the dose gradually with the hospitalized patient and then discharge to continue ambulatory (Siegfried, 2008). The French start at the maximum dose, without progressive increase, keeping the patient monitored for a few hours (Sans, 2009). In our experience, progressive outpatient setup dosing was safe and effective, avoiding serious adverse events. Another concern in the literature has been the possible occurrence of hypoglycemia, although only anecdotal reports associate the use of propranolol with this event. We performed a routine blood glucose test, as well as cardiac evaluation (physical examination and chest X-ray) and abdominal ultrasonography (to detect visceral lesions), as well as transfontanelar ultrasonography in young infants. We did not identify any cases of hypoglycaemia, hypotension or bradycardia that necessitated discontinuation of treatment. Some patients, however, did not tolerate a dose greater than 1-2 mg/kg/day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The optimal treatment of complicated childhood hemangiomas should be rapid, effective and safe, and perhaps the advent of beta-blockers is the answer to this need. Clinical trials are under way worldwide to clarify their efficacy and safety. At first glance, the existing alternatives do not have characteristics that can rival this new treatment, due to the lack of quality evidence and the high profile of adverse effects (for example, high-dose corticosteroids). It should be noted, however, that propranolol showed efficacy in typical infantile hemangiomas in the proliferative phase. There is no evidence yet of effect on hemangiomas of children outside this age group (although our preliminary results corroborate good response to residual lesions as well). To date, there are no reports of use of this drug in other types of hemangiomas (cavernomas, hemangioendotheliomas), nor in lymphangiomas or mixed complex lesions. Isolated cases that we are following indicate that the latter lesions are refractory to propranolol. We are planning a clinical trial to evaluate the response of patients with typical childhood hemangiomas treated with beta-blockers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, infantile hemangiomas are common and most of the lesions involute with time, not justifying treatment. Despite maternal anxiety, expectant behavior should be advocated in most cases. Topical or intralesional treatments are seemingly ineffective, as well as countless non-scientific treatments (such as topical silver nitrate, prescribed to a patient!). The fact that it is a self-limiting disease in most cases leads to the false impression of efficacy for many potentially harmful treatments that should be avoided. Complicated cases should be treated, the first choice is still oral corticosteroid at high dose, the second choice is vincristine for refractory cases. The recent introduction of propranolol promises to modify the landscape of the treatment of these lesions, being fast, effective and safe. The treatment should ideally be through referral to specialized services. In the future, however, treatment with beta-blockers may become a therapy used in primary care for such lesions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="references"&gt;References:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adams DM, Wentzel MS. The Role of the Hematologist/Oncologist in the Care of Patients with Vascular Anomalies. Pediatr Clin  N Am 2008;55:339-355.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Barlow CF, Priebe CJ, Mulliken JB, et al. Spastic diplegia as a complication of interferon alfa-2a treatment of hemangiomas of infancy. J Pediatr 1998;132:527–30.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boon LM, MacDonald DM, Muliken JB. Complications of systemic corticosteroid therapy for problematic hemangioma. Plast Reconstr Surg 1999;104:1616–23.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Curado JH. Tratamento dos hemangiomas e linfangiomas. In: Mélega JM, Zanini AS, Psillakis JM, editores. Cirurgia Plástica: reparadora e estética. 2a. ed., São Paulo: MEDSI; 1992. p. 177.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ezekowitz RAB, Mulliken JB, Folkman J. Interferon alfa-2a therapy for life-threatening hemangiomas of infancy. N Engl J Med 1992;326:1456– 63 [errata: N Engl J Med 1994;330:300, N Engl J Med 1995;333: 595–6].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haggstrom AN, Drolet BA, Baselga E, Chamlin SL, Garzon MC, Horii KA, Lucky AW, Mancini AJ, Metry DW, Newell B, Nopper AJ, Frieden IJ. Prospective study of infantile hemangiomas: demographic, prenatal, and perinatal characteristics. J Pediatr. 2007;150(3):291-294.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haggstrom AN, Drolet BA, Baselga E, Chamlin SL, Garzon MC, Horii KA, Lucky AW, Mancini AJ, Metry DW, Newell B, Nopper AJ, Frieden IJ. Prospective study of infantile hemangiomas: clinical characteristics predicting complications and treatment. Pediatrics. 2006;118(3):882-887.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holmes WJ, Mishra A, Gorst C, Liew SH. Propranolol as first-line treatment for rapidly proliferating Infantile Haemangiomas. J Plast Reconstr Aesthet Surg. 2011 Apr;64(4):445-451&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Léauté-Labrèze C, Dumas de la Roque E, Hubiche T, et al. Propranolol for severe hemangiomas of infancy. N Engl J Med 2008;358:2649-2651.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marler JJ, Mulliken JB. Current management of hemangiomas and vascular malformations. Clin Plastic Surg 2005;32:99-116.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perez J, Pardo J, Gomez C. Vincristine—an effective treatment of corticoid-resistant life-threatening infantile hemangiomas. Acta Oncol 2002;41:197-199.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pope E, Krafchik BR, Macarthur C, Ho N, Baruchel S. Oral Versus High-Dose Pulse Corticosteroids for Problematic Infantile Hemangiomas: A Randomized, Controlled Trial. Pediatrics 2007;119:e1239-e1247.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadan N, Wolach B. Treatment of hemangiomas with high doses of prednisone. J Pediatr 1996;128:947-948.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sans V, de la Roque ED, Berge J, Grenier N, Boralevi F, Mazereeuw-Hautier J, Lipsker D, Dupuis E, Ezzedine K, Vergnes P, Taïeb A, Léauté-Labrèze C. Propranolol for severe infatile hemangiomas: follow-up report. Pediatrics. 2009;124:e423-e431&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Siegfried EC, Keenan WJ, Al-Jureidini S. More on propranolol for hemangiomas of infancy. N Engl J Med 2008;359:2846, author reply 2846–2847&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally published in Rev. Saúde Criança Adolesc., 3 (2): 39-45, jul./dez., 2011 [Portuguese], http://bit.ly/alt-pub2zH&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="article"></category></entry><entry><title>Why do we need open clinical science</title><link href="https://fhcflx.github.io/alt-pub/why-do-we-need-open-clinical-science.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-13T16:03:45-03:00</published><updated>2016-07-13T16:03:45-03:00</updated><author><name>Francisco H C Felix</name></author><id>tag:fhcflx.github.io,2016-07-13:/alt-pub/why-do-we-need-open-clinical-science.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/fhcflx/alt-pub/releases?colorB=dd4814"&gt;&lt;img alt="GitHub release" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/release-v1.0.4-blue.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1133188"&gt;&lt;img alt="Project DOI" src="https://zenodo.org/badge/DOI/10.5281/zenodo.1133188.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.5435968"&gt;&lt;img alt="Article DOI" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/ARTICLE--DOI-10.6084/m9.figshare.5435968-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fhcflx/alt-pub/blob/master/content/docs/Felix_2016-07-13-Why-do-we-need-open-clinical-science.pdf?raw=True"&gt;&lt;img alt="pdf" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/pdf-download-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post that shows an open clinical research model presents the main concepts about the Open Science movement and its implications in clinical research. An outline of what is beginning to be set up as an Open Clinical Research is depicted, drawing attention to its potential benefits to medical …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/fhcflx/alt-pub/releases?colorB=dd4814"&gt;&lt;img alt="GitHub release" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/release-v1.0.4-blue.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1133188"&gt;&lt;img alt="Project DOI" src="https://zenodo.org/badge/DOI/10.5281/zenodo.1133188.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.5435968"&gt;&lt;img alt="Article DOI" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/ARTICLE--DOI-10.6084/m9.figshare.5435968-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fhcflx/alt-pub/blob/master/content/docs/Felix_2016-07-13-Why-do-we-need-open-clinical-science.pdf?raw=True"&gt;&lt;img alt="pdf" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/pdf-download-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post that shows an open clinical research model presents the main concepts about the Open Science movement and its implications in clinical research. An outline of what is beginning to be set up as an Open Clinical Research is depicted, drawing attention to its potential benefits to medical science and the community in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="more-transparency-in-clinical-research"&gt;More transparency in clinical research&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reasons why &lt;a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clinical_research"&gt;clinical research&lt;/a&gt; is done should be obvious. However, one must address them and try to summarize them into a few working principles if an in depth analysis is to be carried out. It is probably a consensus that clinical research aims to develop new treatments for ailments. That said, it should be a corollary that clinical research seeks the benefit of the public. Additionally, it is paramount to clinical research the protection of the experimental subject.
In other words, the individuals that participate in clinical research must not be submitted to unethical or inhumane conditions or procedures, and this includes their privacy. A third principle could be stated as follows: clinical research must adhere to a rigid methodology in order to ensure the highest possible likelihood of reliability of the results. Methodology and reporting have to be clear enough so these results may be fully reproducible by third parties. This will guarantee that the resources spent in the research are not wasted in futile efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leads us to a set of three principles one could summarize as goes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uphold the interest of the public.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protect the integrity of the participant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow a strict, reproducible method.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the best way to ascertain that all clinical research will adopt these principles to the heart? The answer is very difficult, and no one has ever succeeded completely in this intent, as far as I know. A series of reasons complicates the prospect of clinical research, but the most important seem to be conflicts of interest from funders and scientists. However, one may not underestimate the influence of widespread cultural beliefs of science makers and the general public and a pervasive unfamiliarity with the meaning and shortcomings of statistical methods. These are not really small problems. The net result of the clinical research difficulties are low probability of publication of final results of clinical trials (even when they are clinically meaningful), and overall lack of transparency of information derived from clinical trials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to revert this situation? There are many initiatives and propositions that try to address this problem. Briefly, one can divide them in two wide sets or groups: weak (conservative) reform models or strong (non-conservative) reform models. Both aim the same thing: optimize the information productive chain in clinical research. Information can be viewed as an asset, the most important one in this kind of model. The problem can be stated as one of inefficient utilization of this asset. Conservative models generally do not propose major changes in the way information is generated and monetized, but try to effect a discipline upon the agents of this production chain. One can have property of information, but will have to conform to a series of good practices. These practices include mostly registering the clinical research (trial) and its results. Non-conservative models, on the contrary, defy the paradigm of information generation, monetization and ownership. They are based on the idea that information is a property of all people. These models argue against ownership of information by individuals or collectives, and advocate the widespread use of open publication of information in the world wide web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good example of conservative initiatives are the legislation of many countries that specificaly asks the registering of any and all clinical trials. Brazil is an example of this kind of regulation. Prior to the approval of any clinical research by an Institutional Review Board, it has to be registered in Plataforma Brasil, a centralized registry for any clinical or pre-clinical research project in the country, maintained by the Ministry of Health. However, there is little (if at all) enforcement of the law in Brasil, and a great number of clinical research projects that are registered ends up never reporting if it was concluded or have any results. This is far from ideal. An international, independent initiative that can be grouped in the conservative tier is Ben Goldacre&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="http://alltrials.net"&gt;AllTrials.net&lt;/a&gt;, a non-governamental organization of leading science editorial groups and many others devoted to spread the message: &amp;ldquo;all trials registered, all results published&amp;rdquo;. The common point of conservative-type models is that the axis of pharma business funding, science editorial traditional business and ivy league institutions with business-tied research activity is not even mentioned, let alone questioned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notwithstanding that, virtually all &amp;ldquo;first-tier&amp;rdquo; scientific publications are produced in this mainstream information productive chain. They are funded by big pharma, carried out by selected highly regarded institutions and reported in the most traditional and difficult to publish scientific journals. As a correlate measure of influence of this axis, we can examine the distribution of the Thomson Reuters Impact Factor. Less than 0.1% of 2014 published papers were really highly cited, a fact that shapes the landscape of impact factor distribution and, consequently, the rank of the most prestigious journals. That highly redundant, positive feedback loop system concentrates the majority of important clinical research. As a logical conclusion, one can state that most problems with clinical science transparency arise in this axis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This perception has fueled non-conservative initiatives that aim at this very central structure of clinical research. In the last few years, these largely independent and loosely related programs have coalesced in the concept of Open Science. The conceptualization of Open Science has evolved from an analogy to open source software and into a complex idea mainly based on information transparency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-is-open-science"&gt;What is Open Science?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="taxonomy" src="https://s3-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/pfigshare-u-previews/2250225/preview.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the &lt;a href="https://www.fosteropenscience.eu"&gt;Foster (Facilitate Open Science Training for European Research)&lt;/a&gt; initiative site, open science is &lt;code&gt;an umbrella term that involves various movements aiming to remove the barriers for sharing any kind of output, resources, methods or tools, at any stage of the research process&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.1508606.v3"&gt;Knoth, 2015&lt;/a&gt;). Such a concept is open and evolving, and aggregates the free sharing of science production as a whole, encompassing all its multiple phases. From the benchside to the final applications. It&amp;rsquo;s far outstreaching than conceptually narrower conservative initiatives. Even though most of the focus remains on Open Data and Open Access publication, OS is far more than this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://OECD.org"&gt;OECD (Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development)&lt;/a&gt; states that Open Science is &lt;code&gt;to make the primary outputs of publicly funded research results – publications and the research data – publicly accessible in digital format with no or minimal restriction&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1787/5jrs2f963zs1-en"&gt;OECD, 2015&lt;/a&gt;). Notwithstanding this, its outreach is much wider, and extends to the whole science production cycle (&lt;a href="https://www.fosteropenscience.eu/content/what-open-science-introduction"&gt;Fuente, 2016&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="cycle" src="https://www.fosteropenscience.eu/sites/default/files/images/OpenScienceResearchInitiative-ResearchLifecycle.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic concept behind Open Science is that of spreading the scientific knowledge. Actually, this idea can be traced back to the Ancient Library of Alexandria, whose main purpose was to collect all the world&amp;rsquo;s knowledge at its time, under the patronage of the ruler of macedonian Egypt. Although the beginning of &lt;em&gt;open science&lt;/em&gt; as a conceptual framework has been traditionally ascribed to the birth of academic journals in 17th century, the idea of disseminating knowledge is clearly of very ancient origin in ocidental tradition. One of its predecessors may have been the teachings of Aristotle at Athens&amp;rsquo;s Lyceum in the 4th century BC. He introduced the notion of cooperative research and systematic collection of empiric observations (Lindberg, 1992).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notwithstanding the breakthrough brought by the invention of the press in XV century and the academic journals in the XVII century, only in the 40s did the sociologist Robert King Merton clearly defined the notion of common ownership of scientific discoveries. In his view, science achievements are a product of social collaborarion and must be assigned to the community. The system of peer-review and subscription-based scholarly publications that has long been the standard, has been shaken recently. The development of digital tools of information and communication technologies has introduced a new disruptive element in the scientific productive cycle. In a 2009 essay (&lt;a href="http://www.nybooks.com/articles/2009/08/13/the-news-about-the-internet/"&gt;Massing, 2009&lt;/a&gt;), journalist Michael Massing has refered to the analogy between the introduction of the printing press and the advent of the internet (attibuted to NYU&amp;rsquo;s Clay Shirsky):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The historical analogy can be taken a step further: just as the advent of printing helped break the medieval Church’s hold on the flow of information, so is the rise of the Internet loosening the grip of the corporate-owned mass media. A profound if unsettling process of decentralization and democratization is taking place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The term &lt;strong&gt;Open Science&lt;/strong&gt; would be introduced in 2003 by the economist Paul David. trying to analyse the relation between the scientific production by the public sector and the rise of intellectual property rights of information assets. Although still a loosely defined concept with multiply interpretations, the Open Science movement has gained momentum all over the world, and policy makers and researchers are talking about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-about-open-clinical-science"&gt;What about open clinical science?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The logical product of the direct application of open science tenets to clinical research would be something like &lt;em&gt;open clinical science&lt;/em&gt;. Is there anything like open science in clinical research at all? Actually, there is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cardiologist &lt;a href="https://www.forbes.com/forbes/2010/0927/opinions-harlan-krumholz-yale-medicine-ideas-opinions.html"&gt;Harlan Krumholz&lt;/a&gt;, better known for his endless crusade for point-of-care quality and patient-oriented outcomes that reshaped modern medicine, is probably one of the pioneers of &lt;em&gt;open science&lt;/em&gt; in clinical research, or what we could really call &lt;strong&gt;open clinical science&lt;/strong&gt;. Studying unpublished data obtained from litigation, he could show that Merck had data proving Vioxx (rofecoxib) to raise cardiovascular deaths way before it was withdrawn from the market. Cases like this led him and many others that followed to propose the disclosure of all clinical data in public databases, much like the central tenet of &lt;em&gt;open science&lt;/em&gt;. Dr Krumholz has put forward a set of rules (&amp;lsquo;steps&amp;rsquo; as he worded) that the minimal to &amp;lsquo;to bring data sharing and open science into the mainstream of clinical research&amp;rsquo; (&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1161/CIRCOUTCOMES.112.965848"&gt;Krumholz, 2012&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post, in the public domain, the study protocol for each published trial. The protocol should be comprehensive and include policies and procedures relevant to actions taken in the trial.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop mechanisms for those who own trial data to share their raw data and individual patient data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Encourage industry to commit to place all its clinical research data relevant to approved products in the public domain. This action would acknowledge that the privilege of selling products is accompanied by a responsibility to share all the clinical research data relevant to the products&amp;rsquo; benefits and harms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop a culture within academics that values data sharing and open science. After a period in which the original investigators can complete their funded studies, the data should be de-identified and made available for investigators globally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify, within all systematic reviews, trials that are not published, using sources such as clinicaltrials.gov and regulatory postings to determine what is missing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Share data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The importance of sharing all clinical data must be adequately stressed. Data (&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.i637"&gt;Chen, 2016&lt;/a&gt;) show that less than half of all clinical trials are published up to 2 years from their completion, and this includes those with public funding. Trials with negative results are less likely to be published as well. A study has demonstrated that almost all meta-analyses they examined would have their conclusions affected by unpublished data. Even though the focus has been on high methodological quality standards for clinical trials, no elegant method can compensate for missing data, as Dr Krumholz states. A recent systematic review (&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.h5002"&gt;Fleetcroft, 2015&lt;/a&gt;) of heart failure was hampered because of poor reporting and non-disclosure of data, although the pivotal clinical studies had already been done. An attempt to review (&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2014.9646"&gt;Ebrahim, 2014&lt;/a&gt;) reanalyses of randomized controled trials has led to the disturbing conclusion that they are exceedingly rare and methodologically flawed, nevertheless suggesting that the original trials results could lead to different conclusions. Science is based upon the very possibility of hypotheses test and re-test, but this seems not to be the rule in clinical science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A survey (&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.e7570"&gt;Rathi, 2012&lt;/a&gt;) among clinical trialists has shown strong support to share de-identified data. However, the community raised a number of concerns: how to ensure appropriate data use, protection of investigator or funder interests, and protection of research subjects. This suggests that the academic community is ready for &lt;em&gt;open clinical science&lt;/em&gt; but demands a proper platform to lead it safely for all parties involved. Such a platform may already been born in the Yale University Open Data Access (YODA) project, that published (&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7326/0003-4819-158-12-201306180-00009"&gt;Krumholz, 2013&lt;/a&gt;) its first patient-level open clinical data comprehensive reports in 2013. The oldest institutional patient-level data sharing policy may be that from the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI) (&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/1745-6215-14-201"&gt;Coady, 2013&lt;/a&gt;), which repository has data on more than 560,000 participants from 100 clinical trials and observational studies held since 1989. Its policy evolved with time, and set a number of limitations on the sharing and utilization of patient data, making it not truly open access. Many doubt, however, that &lt;em&gt;true open science&lt;/em&gt; is feasible in clinical science (&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/ehjqcco/qcv019"&gt;Flather, 2015&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless the critics and the skeptical, it has became evident that we need a better clinical science to guide bedside clinical decisions. It is not a question of the feasibility of it, it is more of when we are going to implement &lt;em&gt;open clinical science&lt;/em&gt; for the better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clinical_research"&gt;Clinical research, Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://alltrials.net"&gt;AllTrials.net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.fosteropenscience.eu"&gt;Facilitate Open Science Training for European Research, FOSTER&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://OECD.org"&gt;Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, OECD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.forbes.com/forbes/2010/0927/opinions-harlan-krumholz-yale-medicine-ideas-opinions.html"&gt;Harper, Matthew. The most powerful doctor you never heard of. Forbes, 09/09/2010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="references"&gt;References:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.1508606.v3"&gt;Knoth, Petr; Pontika, Nancy (2015): Open Science Taxonomy. figshare.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1787/5jrs2f963zs1-en"&gt;OECD (2015), “Making Open Science a Reality”, OECD Science, Technology and Industry Policy Papers, No. 25, OECD Publishing, Paris&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gemma Bueno de la Fuente. What is open science? Introduction. &lt;a href="https://www.fosteropenscience.eu/content/what-open-science-introduction"&gt;webpage&lt;/a&gt;, retrieved in 10/15/2016.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Promoting openness at different stages of the research process (figure). Open Science and Research Initiative (2014). Open Science and Research Handbook. [English version] Available at &lt;a href="https://avointiede.fi/documents/14273/0/Open+Science+and+Research+Handbook+v.1.0/50316d5d-440b-4496-b039-2997663afff8"&gt;webpage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lindberg, David C. (2007) [1992]. &amp;ldquo;4: Hellenistic Natural Philosophy&amp;rdquo;. The Beginnings of Western Science (2nd ed.). Chicago: University of Chicago Press. ISBN 0-226-48205-7.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nybooks.com/articles/2009/08/13/the-news-about-the-internet/"&gt;Massing, Michael. The news about the internet. The New York Review of Books, August 13, 2009.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1161/CIRCOUTCOMES.112.965848"&gt;Krumholz, HM. Open Science and Data Sharing in Clinical Research Basing Informed Decisions on the Totality of the Evidence. Circulation: Cardiovascular Quality and Outcomes. 2012;5:141-142&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.i637"&gt;Chen, R &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. Publication and reporting of clinical trial results: cross sectional analysis across academic medical centers. BMJ 2016; 352 doi:10.1136/bmj.i637&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.h5002"&gt;Fleetcroft, R &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. Difficulty accessing data from randomised trials of drugs for heart failure: a call for action. BMJ 2015; 351 doi:10.1136/bmj.h5002&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2014.9646"&gt;Ebrahim  S, Sohani  ZN, Montoya  L,  et al.  Reanalyses of randomized clinical trial data.  JAMA 2014 doi:10.1001/jama.2014.9646&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.e7570"&gt;Rathi, V &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. Sharing of clinical trial data among trialists: a cross sectional survey. BMJ 2012; 345 doi:10.1136/bmj.e7570&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7326/0003-4819-158-12-201306180-00009"&gt;Krumholz, HM &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. A Historic Moment for Open Science: The Yale University Open Data Access Project and Medtronic. Ann Intern Med. 2013;158(12):910-911 doi: 10.7326/0003-4819-158-12-201306180-00009&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/1745-6215-14-201"&gt;Coady, SA &amp;amp; Wagner E. Sharing individual level data from observational studies and clinical trials: a perspective from NHLBI. Trials 2013 14:201 doi:10.1186/1745-6215-14-201&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/ehjqcco/qcv019"&gt;Flather, M. Open access data sharing from clinical trials: is it really feasible? Eur Heart J - Qual Care Clin Outcomes, 2015 1(2):49–50, doi:10.1093/ehjqcco/qcv019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally posted on: http://fhcflx.github.io/valkyrie/open-clinical-science/&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="blog post"></category></entry><entry><title>Alternative types of academic publications</title><link href="https://fhcflx.github.io/alt-pub/alternative-types-of-academic-publication.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-06-30T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2016-06-30T00:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Francisco H C Felix</name></author><id>tag:fhcflx.github.io,2016-06-30:/alt-pub/alternative-types-of-academic-publication.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/fhcflx/alt-pub/releases"&gt;&lt;img alt="GitHub release" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/release-v1.0.4-blue.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1133188"&gt;&lt;img alt="Project DOI" src="https://zenodo.org/badge/DOI/10.5281/zenodo.1133188.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.5435977"&gt;&lt;img alt="article doi" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/ARTICLE--DOI-10.6084/m9.figshare.5435977-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fhcflx/alt-pub/blob/master/content/docs/Felix_2016_alt-pub-en.pdf?raw=True"&gt;&lt;img alt="pdf" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/pdf-download-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A whitepaper describing alternative modalities for publication of academic material as diverse as commentaries, preprints, raw research data, conference posters, and many more. A lot of examples from my own bibliography are depicted, along with their citation data, showing that this kind of alternative academic autopublishing can be fully trackable …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/fhcflx/alt-pub/releases"&gt;&lt;img alt="GitHub release" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/release-v1.0.4-blue.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1133188"&gt;&lt;img alt="Project DOI" src="https://zenodo.org/badge/DOI/10.5281/zenodo.1133188.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.5435977"&gt;&lt;img alt="article doi" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/ARTICLE--DOI-10.6084/m9.figshare.5435977-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fhcflx/alt-pub/blob/master/content/docs/Felix_2016_alt-pub-en.pdf?raw=True"&gt;&lt;img alt="pdf" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/pdf-download-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A whitepaper describing alternative modalities for publication of academic material as diverse as commentaries, preprints, raw research data, conference posters, and many more. A lot of examples from my own bibliography are depicted, along with their citation data, showing that this kind of alternative academic autopublishing can be fully trackable and citable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, the paradigm of scientific publication involves primarily the model of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peer_review"&gt;peer-reviewed&lt;/a&gt; publications. Dominated by a few companies and institutions, this model is based on scientific journals that publish in print, on the Internet, or both, works that go through a laborious selection of quality. Initially, an editorial board evaluates the overall quality of submissions, their suitability to the journal editorial line, its apparent scientific soundness, the general design and interest to the audience of the journal. After this highly subjective filter, the unpublished manuscripts are still sent to technical reviewers, usually people with deep knowledge about the area of the submission. At least two of these reviewers are commissioned by the editors. If both accept the task and approve the manuscript, it is submitted for publication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The traditional academic publishing model is based on readers&amp;rsquo; journals, institutions (universities, governments, companies) and libraries that acquire paid signatures. It is an organized and highly profitable industry, as well as an effective oligopoly (1), in which the top five publishing groups control 50% of all publications and have a combined $ 10 billion in profit (1). This was not always a giant business, though. Academic journals are the main channel of scientific dissemination since the 19th century. Until World War II, however, they were mainly published by scientific societies. Only after that did the private academic publishing industry consolidate. Currently, most of the former publishers and journals of scientific societies have been acquired by private companies (1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several authors have pointed out that the academic &lt;em&gt;corpus&lt;/em&gt; represented by scientific publications is dominated by a group of western countries, and this &lt;em&gt;corpus&lt;/em&gt; is commonly referred to as &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;mainstream science&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, whereas, in contrast, the rest of the academic world represents &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;peripheral science&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. This arbitrary division can be roughly compared with the economic classification often identified as &lt;em&gt;dependency theory&lt;/em&gt; that divides the world into &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;central (core)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;peripheral countries&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Thus, the current academic editorial model largely reflects the geographical division between &lt;em&gt;developed&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;underdeveloped&lt;/em&gt; countries, using the World Bank criterion (2,3). This practice does not remain at this level only, down to a layer of institutions of &lt;strong&gt;excellence&lt;/strong&gt; and up to the level of individual researchers, and serves as a positive feedback mechanism to maintain &lt;strong&gt;hegemony&lt;/strong&gt; in the academic world (4). Briefly, &lt;em&gt;elite researchers&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;em&gt;leading institutions&lt;/em&gt; publish in the &lt;em&gt;most renowned journals&lt;/em&gt;. The order can be modified randomly: the &lt;em&gt;most renowned journals&lt;/em&gt; are those where &lt;em&gt;elite researchers&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;leading institutions&lt;/em&gt; are published. It is a self-referenced, closed self-centered model. Popularly, scientists refer to this rank of journals, institutions and researchers as &lt;em&gt;first tier&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;second tier&lt;/em&gt; and even &lt;em&gt;third tier&lt;/em&gt;, terms closely related to economic power (5), but used imprecisely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="problems-in-paradise"&gt;Problems in paradise.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A number of problems afflict the peer reviewed publishing model. The bias imposed by the initial editorial evaluation is pretty obvious, but largely overlooked in discussions on the subject. The editors of a journal, as a rule, print its brand on the editorial line of the journal, often remarkably, however, not always impartially. It&amp;rsquo;s really hard to imagine that in a scenario where there are thousands of scientific journals disputing among themselves a big market impartiality can be maintained systematically. The bias in scientific publications has a name: &lt;strong&gt;publication bias&lt;/strong&gt; (5). It is often invoked when researchers from less important or peripheral centers can not reach the mainstream of academic publications almost exclusively based in developed countries. However, more subtle forms of &amp;ldquo;publication bias&amp;rdquo; are even more common, though less visible. Negative results, for example, rarely reach the top journals, as opposed to &amp;ldquo;revealing findings.&amp;rdquo; The systematic failure to publish negative results seem to affect significantly, for example, the health sciences. Clinical studies showing results are easier to publish than those showing no effect of any treatment (7). Although such a complex phenomenon as publication bias is necessarily multifactorial and involves much more than the scientific journal editors, the latter are part of the &amp;ldquo;subjectivity&amp;rdquo; of peer-reviewed publications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another problem often pointed out is the lack of transparency in peer reviews. Usually, reviewers of scientific publications provide an &lt;em&gt;ad hoc&lt;/em&gt; service and are not part of a body of consultant advisers. Moreover, their identities are usually unknown. There is, therefore, little guarantee that the chosen reviewers represent the field of the evaluated manuscript, let alone are well versed in that specific area of study. Furthermore, the peer review system is built to assess methodologically and scientifically the content of manuscripts, but not to detect fraud or misconduct. There are doubts and suspicions about the objectivity and honesty of each party involved in this process, both from the point of view of authors, and reviewers. Several proposals have been forwarded to try to remedy this problem (8).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The peer review model is economically dominated by publishers and journals that charge subscriptions and receive funding from government agencies and scientific societies (9). Almost all of the most important scientific journals are in developed countries and are published exclusively in English, also pointed out as a source of bias, affecting what and how they will publish. Publications in non-english national languages, even if they are among the most spoken in the world, are little read even in their countries of origin, in contrast to scientific publications in English. Although it makes sense for better international communication that there is a universal language, it imposes a necessary obstacle to scientists whose native language is not English (4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="open-access"&gt;Open access&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recent alternative to the classical model of scientific publication by subscription is the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_access"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;open access&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; model in which the publications are available for free on the Internet to be accessed and the cost of publishing is charged from authors or institutions. Scientific publication in Portuguese in Brazil, for example, is dominated by &lt;a href="http://www.scielo.org/php/level.php?lang=en&amp;amp;component=42&amp;amp;item=1"&gt;Scielo&lt;/a&gt;, a repository of open access scientific publications, funded by Brazilian government agencies. The open access model has received constant criticism of interference in the objectivity of the review process because the authors and institutions pay for research publications. Recent attacks disclosed the fragility of the peer review process in the open access model (10). However, it is the fastest growing academic publishing model and all major academic publishing groups today have their open access section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The peer review and publication policies in open access journals are essentially the same as in traditional journals. As in the traditional model, the quality of reviews is commonly criticized, and anecdotal examples of errors exist innumerable (11). The proliferation of open access publishing houses and journals that publish exclusively on electronic media (which considerably increases publication speed and capacity) is also seen as a factor of overload in the peer review system, already weakened by criticism and difficulty in finding reviewers (11). In this way, open access has an image associated with a somewhat more fragile, perhaps insufficient, peer review. Objectively, there is no proof of this kind of idea, mainly because the revisions occur privately and there is no way to quantify or qualify them, much less how to compare the traditional model with open access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the geographical point of view, the open access journals have the reverse situation from the traditional model. Most publications on open access come from countries and institutions considered &lt;em&gt;peripheral&lt;/em&gt;, outside the &lt;em&gt;core&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;mainstream science&lt;/em&gt;. One apparently paradoxical but important detail is that researchers from &lt;em&gt;peripheral&lt;/em&gt; countries (by World Bank criteria) with lower &lt;em&gt;per capita&lt;/em&gt; income are equally likely to pay for open access publications than mainstream researchers, who are often research funded (2). This is seen by some as indicating the greater permissiveness of the open access publishing system. In fact, a comparison showed that the open access journal &lt;em&gt;PLOS One&lt;/em&gt; accepted 70% of the submissions in 2011, while the hybrid journal (conventional publication alongside to open access) &lt;em&gt;Physical Review Letters&lt;/em&gt; published less than 35% in the same period and the traditional journal &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; published only 8% (12).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A frequent criticism of the open access model is in relation to the amounts charged by authors or institutions for the publication of articles. Prices range from US&amp;#36;399 (per author) in the PeerJ paper to US&amp;#36;5,000 (per article) in the journal Cell Reports. In 2011, the academic publishing industry generated US&amp;#36;9.4 billion and published 1.8 million articles in English, at an average cost of US&amp;#36;5000 per article. According to analyzes, discounting the profit margin, the individual cost per article for publishing houses would be around $ 2700. For critics, this figure is artificially inflated and the cost, in fact, may be much lower. That would explain why a company like PeerJ can charge ten times less than others. On the other hand, experts in scientific publishing believe that PeerJ will not be able to maintain a self-sustaining and not much less lucrative business (13).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="enter-the-green-way"&gt;Enter the Green Way&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatives that do not involve financial dilemmas or barriers to science communication have been proposed. A set of disparate publication arrangements can be grouped on the label &lt;strong&gt;green open access&lt;/strong&gt;, where publications are available free to the public on the Internet, but publishing costs are diluted because there is no journal vehicle, replaced by repositories where the authors themselves &amp;ldquo;publish&amp;rdquo; or deposit their work (&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Self-archiving"&gt;self-archiving&lt;/a&gt;). These manuscripts (or other forms of academic work) are not peer-reviewed, nor pass the evaluation of an editorial board. Such repositories are mostly based in universities, although there are hybrid models where a company provides both open access services paid by the authors (also called &lt;strong&gt;golden open access&lt;/strong&gt;) as well as a self-archiving repository. A number of different academic publishing types have emerged, with greater or lesser participation of mediators such as educational institutions, government and business. A popular scholarly publishing portal has as its motto: &amp;ldquo;credit all your research&amp;rdquo; and accepts submissions of any kind of academic material. Some internet services perform a general assessment to determine the quality of the material posted. Some services only publish the material after this evaluation. Other publish immediately any material deposited and only after perform an evaluation. This review differs from the editorial analysis of a scientific journal, being performed only to ensure the academic nature of the deposited material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The recent proliferation of several different channels that allow the publication of academic materials not conventionally included in peer-reviewed publications shows the strength of the phenomenon. Collectively, these channels are part of the &lt;em&gt;Open Science&lt;/em&gt; movement, which seeks to &lt;em&gt;democratize&lt;/em&gt; access to academic information, reducing barriers to the free dissemination of ideas and research results (14). &lt;em&gt;Open Science&lt;/em&gt; can be seen as part of a broader political-academic trend, sometimes called &lt;em&gt;Open Philosophy&lt;/em&gt;, which involves an innovative way of knowing and also a way of interpreting this new way of knowing 14). Yet an evolving term, the &lt;em&gt;Open Science&lt;/em&gt;, has its roots in the movements of &lt;em&gt;free software&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;open source&lt;/em&gt; of Computer Sciences and relies heavily on recent advances in the internet and the media. It is considered a &lt;em&gt;disruptive&lt;/em&gt; innovation in the sense that it tends to change definitively the way we do and disseminate science. The &lt;em&gt;Green Open Access&lt;/em&gt; road has the potential, unlike the most widespread models today, to truly democratize access to information and subvert the &lt;em&gt;core-periphery&lt;/em&gt; dichotomy that is at the heart of the academic world nowadays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the following sections, I will list several different forms of publication of academic material outside the traditional model and also outside of the &lt;em&gt;Golden way&lt;/em&gt; of open access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="green-open-access-publications"&gt;Green open access publications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This listing brings a non-exhaustive set of alternative academic publication formats, with examples from my own material, deposited in multiple channels. There are more and more ways and means of scientific dissemination, and this &lt;em&gt;e-manuscript&lt;/em&gt; (which is already in its fourth version) will continue to be updated periodically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="conference-posters-deposited-in-repositories"&gt;Conference posters deposited in repositories:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Magalhaes R, Felix J, Albuquerque J et al. Evaluation of the analgesic effect of venlafaxine, a serotonin and noradrenaline reuptake inhibitor [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1259 (poster) &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1110985.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1110985.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fontenele J, Freire P, Santos K et al. Focal brainstem tumors: report of patients treated in a brazilian pediatric oncological center [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1363 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1111076.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1111076.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F, Santos K, Freire P et al. Diffuse intrinsic pontine gliomas: report of patients treated in a brazilian pediatric oncological center [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1362 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1111075.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1111075.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Santos K, Lima R, Bastos MV et al. Retrospective evaluation of patients with recurrent brain tumors treated with vinblastine or temozolomide at the Albert Sabin Children&amp;rsquo;s Hospital between 2007-2012 [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1256 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1110982.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1110982.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F, Feitosa M, Bezerra MdC et al. Undifferentiated intracardiac tumor [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1358 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1111073.1"&gt;doi:f1000research.1111073.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F, Freire P, Santos K and Fontenele J. Predictors of survival in children with ependymoma from a single center: using random survival forests [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1209 (poster) &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1110937.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1110937.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F, Mattos JP, Hirth C and Fontenele J. Everolimus for patients with tumors associated with tuberous sclerosis and neurofibromatosis [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1357 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1111072.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1111072.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alves N, Aquino R, Veras I and Felix F. A case of medulloblastoma with late neurologic deterioration [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1343 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1111060.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1111060.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F, Veras I, Nogueira C and Juvenia F. Nimotuzumab in a case of recurrent glioblastoma expressing a new EGFR mutation [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1303 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1111020.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1111020.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F, Veras I, Bacalhau AF and Fontenele J. Nimotuzumab in patients with progressive diffuse intrinsic pontine glioma [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1302 (poster) &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1111019.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1111019.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F and Fontenele J. Chemoradiotherapy with etoposide, cisplatin, and ifosfamide associated with valproic acid for patients with diffuse intrinsic pontine glioma [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1301 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1111018.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1111018.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F, Araújo O, Trompieri N et al. Treatment of pediatric patients with recurrent brain tumors with vinblastine [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1300 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1111017.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1111017.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F, Araújo O, Trompieri N et al. Treatment of pediatric patients with multiply recurrent brain tumors with temozolomide and valproic acid [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1299 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1111016.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1111016.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Barcelos P, Trindade V, Aguiar L et al. Ewing sarcoma in the skull of an infant: case report [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1258 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1110984.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1110984.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trindade V, Barcelos P, Aguiar L et al. Intramedullary granulocytic sarcoma [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1257 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1110983.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1110983.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freire P, Felix F, Santos K et al. Descriptive longitudinal study of pediatric patients with primary brain tumors: establishment of a hospital registry [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1370 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1111083.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1111083.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F, Azevedo JR, Feitosa M et al. Childhood pleuropulmonary blastoma [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1304 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1111021.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1111021.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F, Albuquerque J and Fontenele J. Subependymal Giant Cell Astrocytoma with good response to oral everolimus – a case report [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1233 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1110960.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1110960.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F, Albuquerque J and Fontenele J. Survival analysis ​of pediatric patients with brain tumors using a machine learning method: decision tree analysis by recursive partitioning [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1223 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1110950.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1110950.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F, Veras I, Nogueira C et al. Seizure prophylaxis with valproic acid in pediatric patients with brain tumors [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1210 (poster) &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1110938.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1110938.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="preprints"&gt;Preprints:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sales M, Figueiredo KS, Fontenele JB, Viana GS, Felix FH. (2015) Sibutramine antinociceptive effect in female rodents is not dependent on catecholaminergic signaling. PeerJ PrePrints 3:e1544v2 &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7287/peerj.preprints.1544v2"&gt;doi:10.7287/peerj.preprints.1544v2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figueiredo KS, Sales ML, Fontenele JB, Viana GS, Felix FH. (2015) Valproate antinociceptive and anti-inflammatory effect in female rodents. PeerJ PrePrints 3:e1613v1 &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7287/peerj.preprints.1613v1"&gt;doi:10.7287/peerj.preprints.1613v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="academic-presentations-slides"&gt;Academic presentations (slides):&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F. Management of infantile hemangiomas [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1231 (slides) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1110958.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1110958.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Albuquerque J, Fontenele J and Felix F. Propranolol treatment for children with hemangiomas – final report [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1232 (slides) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1110959.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1110959.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix, Francisco (2015): Clinical treatment of malignant brain tumors in pediatric patients. figshare.
&lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.2007588.v1"&gt;doi:10.6084/m9.figshare.2007588.v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix, Francisco (2015): Clinical treatment of low-grade gliomas in pediatric patients. figshare.
&lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.2007543.v1"&gt;doi:10.6084/m9.figshare.2007543.v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="abstracts-published-in-proceedings-and-deposited-in-repositories"&gt;Abstracts published in proceedings and deposited in repositories:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix, Francisco (2016): Wilms tumor with cardiac extension - case report. [portuguese]. figshare.
&lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.2059830.v1"&gt;doi:10.6084/m9.figshare.2059830.v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="articles-published-in-local-academic-journals-and-deposited-in-repositories"&gt;Articles published in local academic journals and deposited in repositories:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bonavides de Castro, Patrícia; Santos Bruno, Débora; Rodrigues Filho, Filadelfo; Felix, Francisco; Roberto Lavor Porto, Paulo; Odorico de Moraes Filho, Manoel (2016): Evaluation of the Interference of Cyclosporin in the Development of Metastasis in a Low Malignant Murine Tumor [portuguese]. figshare. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.2059851.v1"&gt;doi:10.6084/m9.figshare.2059851.v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix, Francisco (2016): Treatment of hemangioma in pediatric patients. [portuguese]. figshare.
&lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.2059821.v1"&gt;10.6084/m9.figshare.2059821.v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="selfpublished-replies-to-academic-publications"&gt;Selfpublished replies to academic publications:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix, Francisco; Fontenele, Juvenia Bezerra (2016): Statin effect in fibromyalgia syndrome patients may not be easily predictable. figshare. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.3179281.v1"&gt;doi:10.6084/m9.figshare.3179281.v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix, Francisco; Fontenele, Juvenia Bezerra (2016): Side effects of propranolol used for the treatment of hemangiomas of infancy. figshare. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.3175576.v1"&gt;doi:10.6084/m9.figshare.3175576.v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="research-projects-approved-by-institutional-review-boards"&gt;Research projects approved by institutional review boards:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix, Francisco. (2016). Phase IIa (proof of concept) Trial of Valproic Acid with Chemotherapy and Radiotherapy for Patients with Diffuse Intrinsic Pontine Glioma in Childhood and Adolescence - VALQUIRIA. Zenodo. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.44888"&gt;doi:10.5281/zenodo.44888&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix, Francisco. (2016). Retrospective analysis of off-label treatment with beta-blockers in pediatric patients with hemangiomas diagnosed between January and December 2009 at Hospital Infantil Albert Sabin. Zenodo. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.44890"&gt;doi:10.5281/zenodo.44890&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix, Francisco. (2016). Longitudinal observational study of pediatric patients with primary brain tumors: establishment of a hospital-based registry. Zenodo. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.44885"&gt;doi:10.5281/zenodo.44885&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix, Francisco. (2016). Treatment assessment of pediatric brain tumor patients in Hospital Infantil Albert Sabin between 2007-2008 (amended to 2007-2010). Zenodo. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.44253"&gt;doi:10.5281/zenodo.44253&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="monographs-of-undergraduate-students-under-my-supervision-drafts"&gt;Monographs of undergraduate students under my supervision (drafts):&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lima, Rayra A C et al.. (2016). Evaluation of adverse events of chemotherapy in patients with central nervous system tumors: a retrospective study - first major draft release. Zenodo. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.45085"&gt;doi:10.5281/zenodo.45085&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="manuscripts-drafted-in-authorea-integrated-with-github-and-deposited-in-zenodo"&gt;Manuscripts drafted in &lt;a href="authorea.com"&gt;Authorea&lt;/a&gt;, integrated with &lt;a href="github.com"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; and deposited in &lt;a href="zenodo.org"&gt;Zenodo&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Francisco H C Felix. (2016). Modelo de anteprojeto para relato de caso. Zenodo. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.49874"&gt;doi:10.5281/zenodo.49874&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="macros-and-scripts-deposited-in-public-repositories"&gt;Macros and scripts deposited in public repositories:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Francisco H C Felix. (2016). rapadura: ff macro para OOo. Zenodo. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.46239"&gt;doi:10.5281/zenodo.46239&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="pubmed-commons-comments-post-publication-review"&gt;Pubmed Commons comments (post-publication review):&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix, F. (2014). Comment on &amp;ldquo;The response and survival of children with recurrent diffuse intrinsic pontine glioma based on phase II study of antineoplastons A10 and AS2-1 in patients with brainstem glioma.&amp;rdquo; By Burzynski et al. &lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24718705#cm24718705_6838"&gt;PubMed comment cm24718705_6838&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix, F. (2014). Comment on &amp;ldquo;Inadvertent high-dose therapy with temozolomide in a child with recurrent pontine glioma followed by a rapid clinical response but deteriorated after substitution with low-dose therapy.&amp;rdquo; By Wang et al. &lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24732058#cm24732058_7147"&gt;PubMed comment cm24732058_7147&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="pre-publication-review-refereeing"&gt;Pre-publication review (refereeing):&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Francisco H C Felix. (2013). Pre-publication review of &amp;ldquo;Gajjar, S., Mazloom, A., Chintagumpala, M., Mahajan, A., C. Paulino, A. 2014. Secondary Glioblastoma Multiform in a Patient with CHARGE Syndrome and Prior Radiation Therapy for Medulloblastoma. Pediatric Hematology-Oncology, 31: 366&amp;rdquo;. &lt;a href="https://publons.com/review/227398/"&gt;Publons review 227398&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Francisco H C Felix. (2011). Pre-publication review of &amp;ldquo;Madhumita, N., Suhas K., G., Rakesh K., M., Supratim, D., Krishnendu, M. Infection associated hemophagocytic syndrome in childhood tuberculosis: A case report. Journal of Pediatric Infectious Diseases, 5: 91&amp;rdquo;. &lt;a href="https://publons.com/review/234534/"&gt;Publons review 234534&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Francisco H C Felix. (2010). Pre-publication review of &amp;ldquo;H. Solomon, D. 2010. The Comparative Safety of Analgesics in Older Adults With Arthritis. Archives of Internal Medicine, 170: 1968&amp;rdquo;. &lt;a href="https://publons.com/review/227448/"&gt;Publons review 227448&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Francisco H C Felix. (2009). Pre-publication review of &amp;ldquo;Collins, P., Baudo, F., Huth-Kühne, A., Ingerslev, J., M Kessler, C., Castellano, M., Shima, M., St-Louis, J., Lévesque, H. 2010. Consensus recommendations for the diagnosis and treatment of acquired hemophilia A. BMC Research Notes, 3: 161&amp;rdquo;. &lt;a href="https://publons.com/review/227451/"&gt;Publons review 227451&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Francisco H C Felix. (2009). Pre-publication review of &amp;ldquo;R. Meacham, L., A. Sklar, C., Li, S., Liu, Q., Gimpel, N., Yasui, Y., A. Whitton, J., Stovall, M., L. Robison, L., C. Oeffinger, K. 2009. Diabetes Mellitus in Long-term Survivors of Childhood Cancer. Archives of Internal Medicine, 169: 1381&amp;rdquo;. &lt;a href="https://publons.com/review/227452/"&gt;Publons review 227452&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Francisco H C Felix. (2009). Pre-publication review of &amp;ldquo;L. Cox, C., M. Hudson, M., Mertens, A., Oeffinger, K., Whitton, J., Montgomery, M., L. Robison, L. 2009. Medical Screening Participation in the Childhood Cancer Survivor Study. Archives of Internal Medicine, 169: 454&amp;rdquo;. &lt;a href="https://publons.com/review/227467/"&gt;Publons review 227467&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cite as: Francisco H C Felix. (2016). Alternative types of academic publications. Zenodo. 10.5281/zenodo.594582&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="references"&gt;References:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Larivière V, Haustein S, Mongeon P. The Oligopoly of Academic Publishers in
the Digital Era. PLoS One. 2015;10(6):e0127502. doi:
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0127502"&gt;10.1371/journal.pone.0127502&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kieńć, Witold. Authors from the periphery countries choose open access more often. Learned Publishing 2017;30.2: 125-131.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guédon, J-C (2007). Open access and the divide between ‘mainstream’ and ‘peripheral’ science, in Ferreira, S, Mara SP &amp;amp; Targino, M das G (eds.), Como gerir e qualificar revistas científicas, &lt;a href="http://eprints.rclis.org/10778/"&gt;http://eprints.rclis.org/10778/&lt;/a&gt;, accessed in 09/21/2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meriläinen, Susan, et al. &amp;ldquo;Hegemonic academic practices: experiences of publishing from the periphery.&amp;rdquo; Organization 2008; 15.4: 584-597.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cardoso, RV &amp;amp; Meijers, EJ. Contrasts between first-tierand second-tier cities in Europe: a functional perspective, European Planning Studies, 2016; 24:5,996-1015, DOI: &lt;a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/284730738_Contrasts_between_First-tier_and_Second-tier_Cities_in_Europe_a_functional_perspective"&gt;10.1080/09654313.2015.112070&lt;/a&gt; [accessed Sep 21, 2017].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Loureiro, Luiz Victor Maia, Callegaro Filho, Donato, Rocha, Altieres de Arruda, Prado, Bernard Lobato, Mutão, Taciana Sousa, Donnarumma, Carlos del Cistia, &amp;amp; Giglio, Auro del. Existe viés de publicação para artigos brasileiros sobre câncer?. Einstein (São Paulo), 2013; 11(1), 15-22. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1590/S1679-45082013000100005"&gt;https://dx.doi.org/10.1590/S1679-45082013000100005&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dickersin, K.; Chan, S.; Chalmers, T. C.; et al. &amp;ldquo;Publication bias and clinical trials&amp;rdquo;. Controlled Clinical Trials 1987; 8 (4): 343–353. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0197-2456(87)90155-3"&gt;https://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0197-2456(87)90155-3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lee, K. &amp;amp; Bero, L. Increasing accountability. What authors, editors and reviewers should do to improve peer review. Nature 2006 &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature05007"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/nature05007&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ware, M., &amp;amp; Mabe, M. (2015). The STM Report. &lt;a href="http://www.stm-assoc.org/2015_02_20_STM_Report_2015.pdf"&gt;http://www.stm-assoc.org/2015_02_20_STM_Report_2015.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bohannon, John. &amp;ldquo;Who&amp;rsquo;s Afraid of Peer Review?&amp;rdquo;. Science 2013; 342 (6154): 60–65. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.342.6154.60"&gt;https://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.342.6154.60&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arns, M. Open access is tiring out peer reviewers. Nature 2014; 515, 467 &lt;a href="https://doi.org/doi:10.1038/515467a"&gt;doi:10.1038/515467a&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Van Noorden, R. Open access: The true cost of science publishing. Nature 2013; 495, 426–429 &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1038/495426a"&gt;doi:10.1038/495426a&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Davis, P. PeerJ Membership Model and The Paradox Of The Loyal Customer. &lt;a href="https://scholarlykitchen.sspnet.org/2017/05/08/peerj-membership-model-paradox-loyal-customer/"&gt;The Scholarly Kitchen&lt;/a&gt;, accessed in 21/09/2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pinheiro, LVR. Do acesso livre à ciência aberta: conceitos e implicações na comunicação científica. RECIIS – Rev. Eletron. de Comun. Inf. Inov. Saúde. 2014; 8(2): 153-165 &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.3395/reciis.v8i2.946.pt"&gt;doi:10.3395/reciis.v8i2.946.pt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="white paper"></category></entry></feed>