<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Academic publications - Open Science</title><link href="https://fhcflx.github.io/alt-pub/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://fhcflx.github.io/alt-pub/feeds/open-science.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://fhcflx.github.io/alt-pub/</id><updated>2016-07-13T16:03:45-03:00</updated><entry><title>Why do we need open clinical science</title><link href="https://fhcflx.github.io/alt-pub/why-do-we-need-open-clinical-science.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-13T16:03:45-03:00</published><updated>2016-07-13T16:03:45-03:00</updated><author><name>Francisco H C Felix</name></author><id>tag:fhcflx.github.io,2016-07-13:/alt-pub/why-do-we-need-open-clinical-science.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/fhcflx/alt-pub/releases?colorB=dd4814"&gt;&lt;img alt="GitHub release" src="https://img.shields.io/github/release/fhcflx/alt-pub.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.845747"&gt;&lt;img alt="Project DOI" src="https://zenodo.org/badge/DOI/10.5281/zenodo.845747.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.5435968"&gt;&lt;img alt="Article DOI" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/ARTICLE--DOI-10.6084/m9.figshare.5435968-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fhcflx/alt-pub/blob/master/content/docs/Felix_2016-07-13-Why-do-we-need-open-clinical-science.pdf?raw=True"&gt;&lt;img alt="pdf" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/pdf-download-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="more-transparency-in-clinical-research"&gt;More transparency in clinical research&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reasons why &lt;a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clinical_research"&gt;clinical research&lt;/a&gt; is done should be obvious. However, one must address them and try to summarize them into a few working principles if an in depth analysis is to be carried out. It is probably a consensus that clinical research aims to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/fhcflx/alt-pub/releases?colorB=dd4814"&gt;&lt;img alt="GitHub release" src="https://img.shields.io/github/release/fhcflx/alt-pub.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.845747"&gt;&lt;img alt="Project DOI" src="https://zenodo.org/badge/DOI/10.5281/zenodo.845747.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.5435968"&gt;&lt;img alt="Article DOI" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/ARTICLE--DOI-10.6084/m9.figshare.5435968-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fhcflx/alt-pub/blob/master/content/docs/Felix_2016-07-13-Why-do-we-need-open-clinical-science.pdf?raw=True"&gt;&lt;img alt="pdf" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/pdf-download-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="more-transparency-in-clinical-research"&gt;More transparency in clinical research&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reasons why &lt;a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clinical_research"&gt;clinical research&lt;/a&gt; is done should be obvious. However, one must address them and try to summarize them into a few working principles if an in depth analysis is to be carried out. It is probably a consensus that clinical research aims to develop new treatments for ailments. That said, it should be a corollary that clinical research seeks the benefit of the public. Additionally, it is paramount to clinical research the protection of the experimental subject.
In other words, the individuals that participate in clinical research must not be submitted to unethical or inhumane conditions or procedures, and this includes their privacy. A third principle could be stated as follows: clinical research must adhere to a rigid methodology in order to ensure the highest possible likelihood of reliability of the results. Methodology and reporting have to be clear enough so these results may be fully reproducible by third parties. This will guarantee that the resources spent in the research are not wasted in futile efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leads us to a set of three principles one could summarize as goes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uphold the interest of the public.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protect the integrity of the participant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow a strict, reproducible method.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the best way to ascertain that all clinical research will adopt these principles to the heart? The answer is very difficult, and no one has ever succeeded completely in this intent, as far as I know. A series of reasons complicates the prospect of clinical research, but the most important seem to be conflicts of interest from funders and scientists. However, one may not underestimate the influence of widespread cultural beliefs of science makers and the general public and a pervasive unfamiliarity with the meaning and shortcomings of statistical methods. These are not really small problems. The net result of the clinical research difficulties are low probability of publication of final results of clinical trials (even when they are clinically meaningful), and overall lack of transparency of information derived from clinical trials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to revert this situation? There are many initiatives and propositions that try to address this problem. Briefly, one can divide them in two wide sets or groups: weak (conservative) reform models or strong (non-conservative) reform models. Both aim the same thing: optimize the information productive chain in clinical research. Information can be viewed as an asset, the most important one in this kind of model. The problem can be stated as one of inefficient utilization of this asset. Conservative models generally do not propose major changes in the way information is generated and monetized, but try to effect a discipline upon the agents of this production chain. One can have property of information, but will have to conform to a series of good practices. These practices include mostly registering the clinical research (trial) and its results. Non-conservative models, on the contrary, defy the paradigm of information generation, monetization and ownership. They are based on the idea that information is a property of all people. These models argue against ownership of information by individuals or collectives, and advocate the widespread use of open publication of information in the world wide web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good example of conservative initiatives are the legislation of many countries that specificaly asks the registering of any and all clinical trials. Brazil is an example of this kind of regulation. Prior to the approval of any clinical research by an Institutional Review Board, it has to be registered in Plataforma Brasil, a centralized registry for any clinical or pre-clinical research project in the country, maintained by the Ministry of Health. However, there is little (if at all) enforcement of the law in Brasil, and a great number of clinical research projects that are registered ends up never reporting if it was concluded or have any results. This is far from ideal. An international, independent initiative that can be grouped in the conservative tier is Ben Goldacre&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="http://alltrials.net"&gt;AllTrials.net&lt;/a&gt;, a non-governamental organization of leading science editorial groups and many others devoted to spread the message: &amp;ldquo;all trials registered, all results published&amp;rdquo;. The common point of conservative-type models is that the axis of pharma business funding, science editorial traditional business and ivy league institutions with business-tied research activity is not even mentioned, let alone questioned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notwithstanding that, virtually all &amp;ldquo;first-tier&amp;rdquo; scientific publications are produced in this mainstream information productive chain. They are funded by big pharma, carried out by selected highly regarded institutions and reported in the most traditional and difficult to publish scientific journals. As a correlate measure of influence of this axis, we can examine the distribution of the Thomson Reuters Impact Factor. Less than 0.1% of 2014 published papers were really highly cited, a fact that shapes the landscape of impact factor distribution and, consequently, the rank of the most prestigious journals. That highly redundant, positive feedback loop system concentrates the majority of important clinical research. As a logical conclusion, one can state that most problems with clinical science transparency arise in this axis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This perception has fueled non-conservative initiatives that aim at this very central structure of clinical research. In the last few years, these largely independent and loosely related programs have coalesced in the concept of Open Science. The conceptualization of Open Science has evolved from an analogy to open source software and into a complex idea mainly based on information transparency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-is-open-science"&gt;What is Open Science?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="taxonomy" src="https://s3-eu-west-1.amazonaws.com/pfigshare-u-previews/2250225/preview.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the &lt;a href="https://www.fosteropenscience.eu"&gt;Foster (Facilitate Open Science Training for European Research)&lt;/a&gt; initiative site, open science is &lt;code&gt;an umbrella term that involves various movements aiming to remove the barriers for sharing any kind of output, resources, methods or tools, at any stage of the research process&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.1508606.v3"&gt;Knoth, 2015&lt;/a&gt;). Such a concept is open and evolving, and aggregates the free sharing of science production as a whole, encompassing all its multiple phases. From the benchside to the final applications. It&amp;rsquo;s far outstreaching than conceptually narrower conservative initiatives. Even though most of the focus remains on Open Data and Open Access publication, OS is far more than this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://OECD.org"&gt;OECD (Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development)&lt;/a&gt; states that Open Science is &lt;code&gt;to make the primary outputs of publicly funded research results – publications and the research data – publicly accessible in digital format with no or minimal restriction&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1787/5jrs2f963zs1-en"&gt;OECD, 2015&lt;/a&gt;). Notwithstanding this, its outreach is much wider, and extends to the whole science production cycle (&lt;a href="https://www.fosteropenscience.eu/content/what-open-science-introduction"&gt;Fuente, 2016&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="cycle" src="https://www.fosteropenscience.eu/sites/default/files/images/OpenScienceResearchInitiative-ResearchLifecycle.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic concept behind Open Science is that of spreading the scientific knowledge. Actually, this idea can be traced back to the Ancient Library of Alexandria, whose main purpose was to collect all the world&amp;rsquo;s knowledge at its time, under the patronage of the ruler of macedonian Egypt. Although the beginning of &lt;em&gt;open science&lt;/em&gt; as a conceptual framework has been traditionally ascribed to the birth of academic journals in 17th century, the idea of disseminating knowledge is clearly of very ancient origin in ocidental tradition. One of its predecessors may have been the teachings of Aristotle at Athens&amp;rsquo;s Lyceum in the 4th century BC. He introduced the notion of cooperative research and systematic collection of empiric observations (Lindberg, 1992).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notwithstanding the breakthrough brought by the invention of the press in XV century and the academic journals in the XVII century, only in the 40s did the sociologist Robert King Merton clearly defined the notion of common ownership of scientific discoveries. In his view, science achievements are a product of social collaborarion and must be assigned to the community. The system of peer-review and subscription-based scholarly publications that has long been the standard, has been shaken recently. The development of digital tools of information and communication technologies has introduced a new disruptive element in the scientific productive cycle. In a 2009 essay (&lt;a href="http://www.nybooks.com/articles/2009/08/13/the-news-about-the-internet/"&gt;Massing, 2009&lt;/a&gt;), journalist Michael Massing has refered to the analogy between the introduction of the printing press and the advent of the internet (attibuted to NYU&amp;rsquo;s Clay Shirsky):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The historical analogy can be taken a step further: just as the advent of printing helped break the medieval Church’s hold on the flow of information, so is the rise of the Internet loosening the grip of the corporate-owned mass media. A profound if unsettling process of decentralization and democratization is taking place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The term &lt;strong&gt;Open Science&lt;/strong&gt; would be introduced in 2003 by the economist Paul David. trying to analyse the relation between the scientific production by the public sector and the rise of intellectual property rights of information assets. Although still a loosely defined concept with multiply interpretations, the Open Science movement has gained momentum all over the world, and policy makers and researchers are talking about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-about-open-clinical-science"&gt;What about open clinical science?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The logical product of the direct application of open science tenets to clinical research would be something like &lt;em&gt;open clinical science&lt;/em&gt;. Is there anything like open science in clinical research at all? Actually, there is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cardiologist &lt;a href="https://www.forbes.com/forbes/2010/0927/opinions-harlan-krumholz-yale-medicine-ideas-opinions.html"&gt;Harlan Krumholz&lt;/a&gt;, better known for his endless crusade for point-of-care quality and patient-oriented outcomes that reshaped modern medicine, is probably one of the pioneers of &lt;em&gt;open science&lt;/em&gt; in clinical research, or what we could really call &lt;strong&gt;open clinical science&lt;/strong&gt;. Studying unpublished data obtained from litigation, he could show that Merck had data proving Vioxx (rofecoxib) to raise cardiovascular deaths way before it was withdrawn from the market. Cases like this led him and many others that followed to propose the disclosure of all clinical data in public databases, much like the central tenet of &lt;em&gt;open science&lt;/em&gt;. Dr Krumholz has put forward a set of rules (&amp;lsquo;steps&amp;rsquo; as he worded) that the minimal to &amp;lsquo;to bring data sharing and open science into the mainstream of clinical research&amp;rsquo; (&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1161/CIRCOUTCOMES.112.965848"&gt;Krumholz, 2012&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post, in the public domain, the study protocol for each published trial. The protocol should be comprehensive and include policies and procedures relevant to actions taken in the trial.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop mechanisms for those who own trial data to share their raw data and individual patient data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Encourage industry to commit to place all its clinical research data relevant to approved products in the public domain. This action would acknowledge that the privilege of selling products is accompanied by a responsibility to share all the clinical research data relevant to the products&amp;rsquo; benefits and harms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop a culture within academics that values data sharing and open science. After a period in which the original investigators can complete their funded studies, the data should be de-identified and made available for investigators globally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify, within all systematic reviews, trials that are not published, using sources such as clinicaltrials.gov and regulatory postings to determine what is missing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Share data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The importance of sharing all clinical data must be adequately stressed. Data (&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.i637"&gt;Chen, 2016&lt;/a&gt;) show that less than half of all clinical trials are published up to 2 years from their completion, and this includes those with public funding. Trials with negative results are less likely to be published as well. A study has demonstrated that almost all meta-analyses they examined would have their conclusions affected by unpublished data. Even though the focus has been on high methodological quality standards for clinical trials, no elegant method can compensate for missing data, as Dr Krumholz states. A recent systematic review (&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.h5002"&gt;Fleetcroft, 2015&lt;/a&gt;) of heart failure was hampered because of poor reporting and non-disclosure of data, although the pivotal clinical studies had already been done. An attempt to review (&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2014.9646"&gt;Ebrahim, 2014&lt;/a&gt;) reanalyses of randomized controled trials has led to the disturbing conclusion that they are exceedingly rare and methodologically flawed, nevertheless suggesting that the original trials results could lead to different conclusions. Science is based upon the very possibility of hypotheses test and re-test, but this seems not to be the rule in clinical science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A survey (&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.e7570"&gt;Rathi, 2012&lt;/a&gt;) among clinical trialists has shown strong support to share de-identified data. However, the community raised a number of concerns: how to ensure appropriate data use, protection of investigator or funder interests, and protection of research subjects. This suggests that the academic community is ready for &lt;em&gt;open clinical science&lt;/em&gt; but demands a proper platform to lead it safely for all parties involved. Such a platform may already been born in the Yale University Open Data Access (YODA) project, that published (&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7326/0003-4819-158-12-201306180-00009"&gt;Krumholz, 2013&lt;/a&gt;) its first patient-level open clinical data comprehensive reports in 2013. The oldest institutional patient-level data sharing policy may be that from the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI) (&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/1745-6215-14-201"&gt;Coady, 2013&lt;/a&gt;), which repository has data on more than 560,000 participants from 100 clinical trials and observational studies held since 1989. Its policy evolved with time, and set a number of limitations on the sharing and utilization of patient data, making it not truly open access. Many doubt, however, that &lt;em&gt;true open science&lt;/em&gt; is feasible in clinical science (&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/ehjqcco/qcv019"&gt;Flather, 2015&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless the critics and the skeptical, it has became evident that we need a better clinical science to guide bedside clinical decisions. It is not a question of the feasibility of it, it is more of when we are going to implement &lt;em&gt;open clinical science&lt;/em&gt; for the better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="links"&gt;Links:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clinical_research"&gt;Clinical research, Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://alltrials.net"&gt;AllTrials.net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.fosteropenscience.eu"&gt;Facilitate Open Science Training for European Research, FOSTER&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://OECD.org"&gt;Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, OECD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.forbes.com/forbes/2010/0927/opinions-harlan-krumholz-yale-medicine-ideas-opinions.html"&gt;Harper, Matthew. The most powerful doctor you never heard of. Forbes, 09/09/2010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="references"&gt;References:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.1508606.v3"&gt;Knoth, Petr; Pontika, Nancy (2015): Open Science Taxonomy. figshare.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1787/5jrs2f963zs1-en"&gt;OECD (2015), “Making Open Science a Reality”, OECD Science, Technology and Industry Policy Papers, No. 25, OECD Publishing, Paris&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gemma Bueno de la Fuente. What is open science? Introduction. &lt;a href="https://www.fosteropenscience.eu/content/what-open-science-introduction"&gt;webpage&lt;/a&gt;, retrieved in 10/15/2016.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Promoting openness at different stages of the research process (figure). Open Science and Research Initiative (2014). Open Science and Research Handbook. [English version] Available at &lt;a href="https://avointiede.fi/documents/14273/0/Open+Science+and+Research+Handbook+v.1.0/50316d5d-440b-4496-b039-2997663afff8"&gt;webpage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lindberg, David C. (2007) [1992]. &amp;ldquo;4: Hellenistic Natural Philosophy&amp;rdquo;. The Beginnings of Western Science (2nd ed.). Chicago: University of Chicago Press. ISBN 0-226-48205-7.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nybooks.com/articles/2009/08/13/the-news-about-the-internet/"&gt;Massing, Michael. The news about the internet. The New York Review of Books, August 13, 2009.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1161/CIRCOUTCOMES.112.965848"&gt;Krumholz, HM. Open Science and Data Sharing in Clinical Research Basing Informed Decisions on the Totality of the Evidence. Circulation: Cardiovascular Quality and Outcomes. 2012;5:141-142&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.i637"&gt;Chen, R &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. Publication and reporting of clinical trial results: cross sectional analysis across academic medical centers. BMJ 2016; 352 doi:10.1136/bmj.i637&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.h5002"&gt;Fleetcroft, R &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. Difficulty accessing data from randomised trials of drugs for heart failure: a call for action. BMJ 2015; 351 doi:10.1136/bmj.h5002&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2014.9646"&gt;Ebrahim  S, Sohani  ZN, Montoya  L,  et al.  Reanalyses of randomized clinical trial data.  JAMA 2014 doi:10.1001/jama.2014.9646&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.e7570"&gt;Rathi, V &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. Sharing of clinical trial data among trialists: a cross sectional survey. BMJ 2012; 345 doi:10.1136/bmj.e7570&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7326/0003-4819-158-12-201306180-00009"&gt;Krumholz, HM &lt;em&gt;et al&lt;/em&gt;. A Historic Moment for Open Science: The Yale University Open Data Access Project and Medtronic. Ann Intern Med. 2013;158(12):910-911 doi: 10.7326/0003-4819-158-12-201306180-00009&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/1745-6215-14-201"&gt;Coady, SA &amp;amp; Wagner E. Sharing individual level data from observational studies and clinical trials: a perspective from NHLBI. Trials 2013 14:201 doi:10.1186/1745-6215-14-201&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/ehjqcco/qcv019"&gt;Flather, M. Open access data sharing from clinical trials: is it really feasible? Eur Heart J - Qual Care Clin Outcomes, 2015 1(2):49–50, doi:10.1093/ehjqcco/qcv019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally posted on: http://fhcflx.github.io/valkyrie/open-clinical-science/&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="open clinical science"></category><category term="open notebook science"></category></entry><entry><title>Alternative types of academic publications</title><link href="https://fhcflx.github.io/alt-pub/alternative-types-of-academic-publication.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-06-30T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2016-06-30T00:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>Francisco H C Felix</name></author><id>tag:fhcflx.github.io,2016-06-30:/alt-pub/alternative-types-of-academic-publication.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/fhcflx/alt-pub/releases"&gt;&lt;img alt="GitHub release" src="https://img.shields.io/github/release/fhcflx/alt-pub.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.845747"&gt;&lt;img alt="Project DOI" src="https://zenodo.org/badge/DOI/10.5281/zenodo.845747.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.5435977"&gt;&lt;img alt="article doi" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/ARTICLE--DOI-10.6084/m9.figshare.5435977-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fhcflx/alt-pub/blob/master/content/docs/Felix_2016_alt-pub-en.pdf?raw=True"&gt;&lt;img alt="pdf" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/pdf-download-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, the paradigm of scientific publication involves primarily the model of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peer_review"&gt;peer-reviewed&lt;/a&gt; publications. Dominated by a few companies and institutions, this model is based on scientific journals that publish in print, on the Internet, or both, works that go through a laborious selection of quality. Initially, an editorial board …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/fhcflx/alt-pub/releases"&gt;&lt;img alt="GitHub release" src="https://img.shields.io/github/release/fhcflx/alt-pub.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.845747"&gt;&lt;img alt="Project DOI" src="https://zenodo.org/badge/DOI/10.5281/zenodo.845747.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.5435977"&gt;&lt;img alt="article doi" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/ARTICLE--DOI-10.6084/m9.figshare.5435977-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://github.com/fhcflx/alt-pub/blob/master/content/docs/Felix_2016_alt-pub-en.pdf?raw=True"&gt;&lt;img alt="pdf" src="https://img.shields.io/badge/pdf-download-dd4814.svg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, the paradigm of scientific publication involves primarily the model of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peer_review"&gt;peer-reviewed&lt;/a&gt; publications. Dominated by a few companies and institutions, this model is based on scientific journals that publish in print, on the Internet, or both, works that go through a laborious selection of quality. Initially, an editorial board evaluates the overall quality of submissions, their suitability to the journal editorial line, its apparent scientific soundness, the general design and interest to the audience of the journal. After this highly subjective filter, the unpublished manuscripts are still sent to technical reviewers, usually people with deep knowledge about the area of the submission. At least two of these reviewers are commissioned by the editors. If both accept the task and approve the manuscript, it is submitted for publication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The traditional academic publishing model is based on readers&amp;rsquo; journals, institutions (universities, governments, companies) and libraries that acquire paid signatures. It is an organized and highly profitable industry, as well as an effective oligopoly (1), in which the top five publishing groups control 50% of all publications and have a combined $ 10 billion in profit (1). This was not always a giant business, though. Academic journals are the main channel of scientific dissemination since the 19th century. Until World War II, however, they were mainly published by scientific societies. Only after that did the private academic publishing industry consolidate. Currently, most of the former publishers and journals of scientific societies have been acquired by private companies (1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several authors have pointed out that the academic &lt;em&gt;corpus&lt;/em&gt; represented by scientific publications is dominated by a group of western countries, and this &lt;em&gt;corpus&lt;/em&gt; is commonly referred to as &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;mainstream science&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, whereas, in contrast, the rest of the academic world represents &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;peripheral science&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. This arbitrary division can be roughly compared with the economic classification often identified as &lt;em&gt;dependency theory&lt;/em&gt; that divides the world into &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;central (core)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;peripheral countries&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Thus, the current academic editorial model largely reflects the geographical division between &lt;em&gt;developed&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;underdeveloped&lt;/em&gt; countries, using the World Bank criterion (2,3). This practice does not remain at this level only, down to a layer of institutions of &lt;strong&gt;excellence&lt;/strong&gt; and up to the level of individual researchers, and serves as a positive feedback mechanism to maintain &lt;strong&gt;hegemony&lt;/strong&gt; in the academic world (4). Briefly, &lt;em&gt;elite researchers&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;em&gt;leading institutions&lt;/em&gt; publish in the &lt;em&gt;most renowned journals&lt;/em&gt;. The order can be modified randomly: the &lt;em&gt;most renowned journals&lt;/em&gt; are those where &lt;em&gt;elite researchers&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;leading institutions&lt;/em&gt; are published. It is a self-referenced, closed self-centered model. Popularly, scientists refer to this rank of journals, institutions and researchers as &lt;em&gt;first tier&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;second tier&lt;/em&gt; and even &lt;em&gt;third tier&lt;/em&gt;, terms closely related to economic power (5), but used imprecisely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="problems-in-paradise"&gt;Problems in paradise.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A number of problems afflict the peer reviewed publishing model. The bias imposed by the initial editorial evaluation is pretty obvious, but largely overlooked in discussions on the subject. The editors of a journal, as a rule, print its brand on the editorial line of the journal, often remarkably, however, not always impartially. It&amp;rsquo;s really hard to imagine that in a scenario where there are thousands of scientific journals disputing among themselves a big market impartiality can be maintained systematically. The bias in scientific publications has a name: &lt;strong&gt;publication bias&lt;/strong&gt; (5). It is often invoked when researchers from less important or peripheral centers can not reach the mainstream of academic publications almost exclusively based in developed countries. However, more subtle forms of &amp;ldquo;publication bias&amp;rdquo; are even more common, though less visible. Negative results, for example, rarely reach the top journals, as opposed to &amp;ldquo;revealing findings.&amp;rdquo; The systematic failure to publish negative results seem to affect significantly, for example, the health sciences. Clinical studies showing results are easier to publish than those showing no effect of any treatment (7). Although such a complex phenomenon as publication bias is necessarily multifactorial and involves much more than the scientific journal editors, the latter are part of the &amp;ldquo;subjectivity&amp;rdquo; of peer-reviewed publications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another problem often pointed out is the lack of transparency in peer reviews. Usually, reviewers of scientific publications provide an &lt;em&gt;ad hoc&lt;/em&gt; service and are not part of a body of consultant advisers. Moreover, their identities are usually unknown. There is, therefore, little guarantee that the chosen reviewers represent the field of the evaluated manuscript, let alone are well versed in that specific area of study. Furthermore, the peer review system is built to assess methodologically and scientifically the content of manuscripts, but not to detect fraud or misconduct. There are doubts and suspicions about the objectivity and honesty of each party involved in this process, both from the point of view of authors, and reviewers. Several proposals have been forwarded to try to remedy this problem (8).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The peer review model is economically dominated by publishers and journals that charge subscriptions and receive funding from government agencies and scientific societies (9). Almost all of the most important scientific journals are in developed countries and are published exclusively in English, also pointed out as a source of bias, affecting what and how they will publish. Publications in non-english national languages, even if they are among the most spoken in the world, are little read even in their countries of origin, in contrast to scientific publications in English. Although it makes sense for better international communication that there is a universal language, it imposes a necessary obstacle to scientists whose native language is not English (4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="open-access"&gt;Open access&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recent alternative to the classical model of scientific publication by subscription is the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_access"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;open access&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; model in which the publications are available for free on the Internet to be accessed and the cost of publishing is charged from authors or institutions. Scientific publication in Portuguese in Brazil, for example, is dominated by &lt;a href="http://www.scielo.org/php/level.php?lang=en&amp;amp;component=42&amp;amp;item=1"&gt;Scielo&lt;/a&gt;, a repository of open access scientific publications, funded by Brazilian government agencies. The open access model has received constant criticism of interference in the objectivity of the review process because the authors and institutions pay for research publications. Recent attacks disclosed the fragility of the peer review process in the open access model (10). However, it is the fastest growing academic publishing model and all major academic publishing groups today have their open access section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The peer review and publication policies in open access journals are essentially the same as in traditional journals. As in the traditional model, the quality of reviews is commonly criticized, and anecdotal examples of errors exist innumerable (11). The proliferation of open access publishing houses and journals that publish exclusively on electronic media (which considerably increases publication speed and capacity) is also seen as a factor of overload in the peer review system, already weakened by criticism and difficulty in finding reviewers (11). In this way, open access has an image associated with a somewhat more fragile, perhaps insufficient, peer review. Objectively, there is no proof of this kind of idea, mainly because the revisions occur privately and there is no way to quantify or qualify them, much less how to compare the traditional model with open access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the geographical point of view, the open access journals have the reverse situation from the traditional model. Most publications on open access come from countries and institutions considered &lt;em&gt;peripheral&lt;/em&gt;, outside the &lt;em&gt;core&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;mainstream science&lt;/em&gt;. One apparently paradoxical but important detail is that researchers from &lt;em&gt;peripheral&lt;/em&gt; countries (by World Bank criteria) with lower &lt;em&gt;per capita&lt;/em&gt; income are equally likely to pay for open access publications than mainstream researchers, who are often research funded (2). This is seen by some as indicating the greater permissiveness of the open access publishing system. In fact, a comparison showed that the open access journal &lt;em&gt;PLOS One&lt;/em&gt; accepted 70% of the submissions in 2011, while the hybrid journal (conventional publication alongside to open access) &lt;em&gt;Physical Review Letters&lt;/em&gt; published less than 35% in the same period and the traditional journal &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; published only 8% (12).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A frequent criticism of the open access model is in relation to the amounts charged by authors or institutions for the publication of articles. Prices range from US&amp;#36;399 (per author) in the PeerJ paper to US&amp;#36;5,000 (per article) in the journal Cell Reports. In 2011, the academic publishing industry generated US&amp;#36;9.4 billion and published 1.8 million articles in English, at an average cost of US&amp;#36;5000 per article. According to analyzes, discounting the profit margin, the individual cost per article for publishing houses would be around $ 2700. For critics, this figure is artificially inflated and the cost, in fact, may be much lower. That would explain why a company like PeerJ can charge ten times less than others. On the other hand, experts in scientific publishing believe that PeerJ will not be able to maintain a self-sustaining and not much less lucrative business (13).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="enter-the-green-way"&gt;Enter the Green Way&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatives that do not involve financial dilemmas or barriers to science communication have been proposed. A set of disparate publication arrangements can be grouped on the label &lt;strong&gt;green open access&lt;/strong&gt;, where publications are available free to the public on the Internet, but publishing costs are diluted because there is no journal vehicle, replaced by repositories where the authors themselves &amp;ldquo;publish&amp;rdquo; or deposit their work (&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Self-archiving"&gt;self-archiving&lt;/a&gt;). These manuscripts (or other forms of academic work) are not peer-reviewed, nor pass the evaluation of an editorial board. Such repositories are mostly based in universities, although there are hybrid models where a company provides both open access services paid by the authors (also called &lt;strong&gt;golden open access&lt;/strong&gt;) as well as a self-archiving repository. A number of different academic publishing types have emerged, with greater or lesser participation of mediators such as educational institutions, government and business. A popular scholarly publishing portal has as its motto: &amp;ldquo;credit all your research&amp;rdquo; and accepts submissions of any kind of academic material. Some internet services perform a general assessment to determine the quality of the material posted. Some services only publish the material after this evaluation. Other publish immediately any material deposited and only after perform an evaluation. This review differs from the editorial analysis of a scientific journal, being performed only to ensure the academic nature of the deposited material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The recent proliferation of several different channels that allow the publication of academic materials not conventionally included in peer-reviewed publications shows the strength of the phenomenon. Collectively, these channels are part of the &lt;em&gt;Open Science&lt;/em&gt; movement, which seeks to &lt;em&gt;democratize&lt;/em&gt; access to academic information, reducing barriers to the free dissemination of ideas and research results (14). &lt;em&gt;Open Science&lt;/em&gt; can be seen as part of a broader political-academic trend, sometimes called &lt;em&gt;Open Philosophy&lt;/em&gt;, which involves an innovative way of knowing and also a way of interpreting this new way of knowing 14). Yet an evolving term, the &lt;em&gt;Open Science&lt;/em&gt;, has its roots in the movements of &lt;em&gt;free software&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;open source&lt;/em&gt; of Computer Sciences and relies heavily on recent advances in the internet and the media. It is considered a &lt;em&gt;disruptive&lt;/em&gt; innovation in the sense that it tends to change definitively the way we do and disseminate science. The &lt;em&gt;Green Open Access&lt;/em&gt; road has the potential, unlike the most widespread models today, to truly democratize access to information and subvert the &lt;em&gt;core-periphery&lt;/em&gt; dichotomy that is at the heart of the academic world nowadays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the following sections, I will list several different forms of publication of academic material outside the traditional model and also outside of the &lt;em&gt;Golden way&lt;/em&gt; of open access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="green-open-access-publications"&gt;Green open access publications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This listing brings a non-exhaustive set of alternative academic publication formats, with examples from my own material, deposited in multiple channels. There are more and more ways and means of scientific dissemination, and this &lt;em&gt;e-manuscript&lt;/em&gt; (which is already in its fourth version) will continue to be updated periodically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="conference-posters-deposited-in-repositories"&gt;Conference posters deposited in repositories:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Magalhaes R, Felix J, Albuquerque J et al. Evaluation of the analgesic effect of venlafaxine, a serotonin and noradrenaline reuptake inhibitor [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1259 (poster) &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1110985.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1110985.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fontenele J, Freire P, Santos K et al. Focal brainstem tumors: report of patients treated in a brazilian pediatric oncological center [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1363 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1111076.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1111076.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F, Santos K, Freire P et al. Diffuse intrinsic pontine gliomas: report of patients treated in a brazilian pediatric oncological center [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1362 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1111075.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1111075.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Santos K, Lima R, Bastos MV et al. Retrospective evaluation of patients with recurrent brain tumors treated with vinblastine or temozolomide at the Albert Sabin Children&amp;rsquo;s Hospital between 2007-2012 [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1256 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1110982.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1110982.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F, Feitosa M, Bezerra MdC et al. Undifferentiated intracardiac tumor [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1358 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1111073.1"&gt;doi:f1000research.1111073.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F, Freire P, Santos K and Fontenele J. Predictors of survival in children with ependymoma from a single center: using random survival forests [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1209 (poster) &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1110937.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1110937.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F, Mattos JP, Hirth C and Fontenele J. Everolimus for patients with tumors associated with tuberous sclerosis and neurofibromatosis [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1357 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1111072.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1111072.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alves N, Aquino R, Veras I and Felix F. A case of medulloblastoma with late neurologic deterioration [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1343 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1111060.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1111060.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F, Veras I, Nogueira C and Juvenia F. Nimotuzumab in a case of recurrent glioblastoma expressing a new EGFR mutation [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1303 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1111020.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1111020.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F, Veras I, Bacalhau AF and Fontenele J. Nimotuzumab in patients with progressive diffuse intrinsic pontine glioma [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1302 (poster) &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1111019.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1111019.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F and Fontenele J. Chemoradiotherapy with etoposide, cisplatin, and ifosfamide associated with valproic acid for patients with diffuse intrinsic pontine glioma [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1301 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1111018.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1111018.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F, Araújo O, Trompieri N et al. Treatment of pediatric patients with recurrent brain tumors with vinblastine [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1300 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1111017.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1111017.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F, Araújo O, Trompieri N et al. Treatment of pediatric patients with multiply recurrent brain tumors with temozolomide and valproic acid [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1299 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1111016.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1111016.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Barcelos P, Trindade V, Aguiar L et al. Ewing sarcoma in the skull of an infant: case report [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1258 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1110984.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1110984.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trindade V, Barcelos P, Aguiar L et al. Intramedullary granulocytic sarcoma [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1257 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1110983.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1110983.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freire P, Felix F, Santos K et al. Descriptive longitudinal study of pediatric patients with primary brain tumors: establishment of a hospital registry [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1370 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1111083.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1111083.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F, Azevedo JR, Feitosa M et al. Childhood pleuropulmonary blastoma [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1304 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1111021.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1111021.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F, Albuquerque J and Fontenele J. Subependymal Giant Cell Astrocytoma with good response to oral everolimus – a case report [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1233 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1110960.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1110960.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F, Albuquerque J and Fontenele J. Survival analysis ​of pediatric patients with brain tumors using a machine learning method: decision tree analysis by recursive partitioning [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1223 (poster) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1110950.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1110950.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F, Veras I, Nogueira C et al. Seizure prophylaxis with valproic acid in pediatric patients with brain tumors [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1210 (poster) &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1110938.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1110938.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="preprints"&gt;Preprints:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sales M, Figueiredo KS, Fontenele JB, Viana GS, Felix FH. (2015) Sibutramine antinociceptive effect in female rodents is not dependent on catecholaminergic signaling. PeerJ PrePrints 3:e1544v2 &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7287/peerj.preprints.1544v2"&gt;doi:10.7287/peerj.preprints.1544v2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figueiredo KS, Sales ML, Fontenele JB, Viana GS, Felix FH. (2015) Valproate antinociceptive and anti-inflammatory effect in female rodents. PeerJ PrePrints 3:e1613v1 &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7287/peerj.preprints.1613v1"&gt;doi:10.7287/peerj.preprints.1613v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="academic-presentations-slides"&gt;Academic presentations (slides):&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix F. Management of infantile hemangiomas [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1231 (slides) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1110958.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1110958.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Albuquerque J, Fontenele J and Felix F. Propranolol treatment for children with hemangiomas – final report [v1; not peer reviewed]. F1000Research 2015, 4:1232 (slides) [Portuguese] &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.7490/f1000research.1110959.1"&gt;doi:10.7490/f1000research.1110959.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix, Francisco (2015): Clinical treatment of malignant brain tumors in pediatric patients. figshare.
&lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.2007588.v1"&gt;doi:10.6084/m9.figshare.2007588.v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix, Francisco (2015): Clinical treatment of low-grade gliomas in pediatric patients. figshare.
&lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.2007543.v1"&gt;doi:10.6084/m9.figshare.2007543.v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="abstracts-published-in-proceedings-and-deposited-in-repositories"&gt;Abstracts published in proceedings and deposited in repositories:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix, Francisco (2016): Wilms tumor with cardiac extension - case report. [portuguese]. figshare.
&lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.2059830.v1"&gt;doi:10.6084/m9.figshare.2059830.v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="articles-published-in-local-academic-journals-and-deposited-in-repositories"&gt;Articles published in local academic journals and deposited in repositories:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bonavides de Castro, Patrícia; Santos Bruno, Débora; Rodrigues Filho, Filadelfo; Felix, Francisco; Roberto Lavor Porto, Paulo; Odorico de Moraes Filho, Manoel (2016): Evaluation of the Interference of Cyclosporin in the Development of Metastasis in a Low Malignant Murine Tumor [portuguese]. figshare. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.2059851.v1"&gt;doi:10.6084/m9.figshare.2059851.v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix, Francisco (2016): Treatment of hemangioma in pediatric patients. [portuguese]. figshare.
&lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.2059821.v1"&gt;10.6084/m9.figshare.2059821.v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="selfpublished-replies-to-academic-publications"&gt;Selfpublished replies to academic publications:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix, Francisco; Fontenele, Juvenia Bezerra (2016): Statin effect in fibromyalgia syndrome patients may not be easily predictable. figshare. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.3179281.v1"&gt;doi:10.6084/m9.figshare.3179281.v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix, Francisco; Fontenele, Juvenia Bezerra (2016): Side effects of propranolol used for the treatment of hemangiomas of infancy. figshare. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.3175576.v1"&gt;doi:10.6084/m9.figshare.3175576.v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="research-projects-approved-by-institutional-review-boards"&gt;Research projects approved by institutional review boards:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix, Francisco. (2016). Phase IIa (proof of concept) Trial of Valproic Acid with Chemotherapy and Radiotherapy for Patients with Diffuse Intrinsic Pontine Glioma in Childhood and Adolescence - VALQUIRIA. Zenodo. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.44888"&gt;doi:10.5281/zenodo.44888&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix, Francisco. (2016). Retrospective analysis of off-label treatment with beta-blockers in pediatric patients with hemangiomas diagnosed between January and December 2009 at Hospital Infantil Albert Sabin. Zenodo. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.44890"&gt;doi:10.5281/zenodo.44890&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix, Francisco. (2016). Longitudinal observational study of pediatric patients with primary brain tumors: establishment of a hospital-based registry. Zenodo. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.44885"&gt;doi:10.5281/zenodo.44885&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix, Francisco. (2016). Treatment assessment of pediatric brain tumor patients in Hospital Infantil Albert Sabin between 2007-2008 (amended to 2007-2010). Zenodo. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.44253"&gt;doi:10.5281/zenodo.44253&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="monographs-of-undergraduate-students-under-my-supervision-drafts"&gt;Monographs of undergraduate students under my supervision (drafts):&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lima, Rayra A C et al.. (2016). Evaluation of adverse events of chemotherapy in patients with central nervous system tumors: a retrospective study - first major draft release. Zenodo. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.45085"&gt;doi:10.5281/zenodo.45085&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="manuscripts-drafted-in-authorea-integrated-with-github-and-deposited-in-zenodo"&gt;Manuscripts drafted in &lt;a href="authorea.com"&gt;Authorea&lt;/a&gt;, integrated with &lt;a href="github.com"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; and deposited in &lt;a href="zenodo.org"&gt;Zenodo&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Francisco H C Felix. (2016). Modelo de anteprojeto para relato de caso. Zenodo. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.49874"&gt;doi:10.5281/zenodo.49874&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="macros-and-scripts-deposited-in-public-repositories"&gt;Macros and scripts deposited in public repositories:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Francisco H C Felix. (2016). rapadura: ff macro para OOo. Zenodo. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.46239"&gt;doi:10.5281/zenodo.46239&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="pubmed-commons-comments-post-publication-review"&gt;Pubmed Commons comments (post-publication review):&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix, F. (2014). Comment on &amp;ldquo;The response and survival of children with recurrent diffuse intrinsic pontine glioma based on phase II study of antineoplastons A10 and AS2-1 in patients with brainstem glioma.&amp;rdquo; By Burzynski et al. &lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24718705#cm24718705_6838"&gt;PubMed comment cm24718705_6838&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Felix, F. (2014). Comment on &amp;ldquo;Inadvertent high-dose therapy with temozolomide in a child with recurrent pontine glioma followed by a rapid clinical response but deteriorated after substitution with low-dose therapy.&amp;rdquo; By Wang et al. &lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24732058#cm24732058_7147"&gt;PubMed comment cm24732058_7147&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="pre-publication-review-refereeing"&gt;Pre-publication review (refereeing):&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Francisco H C Felix. (2013). Pre-publication review of &amp;ldquo;Gajjar, S., Mazloom, A., Chintagumpala, M., Mahajan, A., C. Paulino, A. 2014. Secondary Glioblastoma Multiform in a Patient with CHARGE Syndrome and Prior Radiation Therapy for Medulloblastoma. Pediatric Hematology-Oncology, 31: 366&amp;rdquo;. &lt;a href="https://publons.com/review/227398/"&gt;Publons review 227398&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Francisco H C Felix. (2011). Pre-publication review of &amp;ldquo;Madhumita, N., Suhas K., G., Rakesh K., M., Supratim, D., Krishnendu, M. Infection associated hemophagocytic syndrome in childhood tuberculosis: A case report. Journal of Pediatric Infectious Diseases, 5: 91&amp;rdquo;. &lt;a href="https://publons.com/review/234534/"&gt;Publons review 234534&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Francisco H C Felix. (2010). Pre-publication review of &amp;ldquo;H. Solomon, D. 2010. The Comparative Safety of Analgesics in Older Adults With Arthritis. Archives of Internal Medicine, 170: 1968&amp;rdquo;. &lt;a href="https://publons.com/review/227448/"&gt;Publons review 227448&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Francisco H C Felix. (2009). Pre-publication review of &amp;ldquo;Collins, P., Baudo, F., Huth-Kühne, A., Ingerslev, J., M Kessler, C., Castellano, M., Shima, M., St-Louis, J., Lévesque, H. 2010. Consensus recommendations for the diagnosis and treatment of acquired hemophilia A. BMC Research Notes, 3: 161&amp;rdquo;. &lt;a href="https://publons.com/review/227451/"&gt;Publons review 227451&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Francisco H C Felix. (2009). Pre-publication review of &amp;ldquo;R. Meacham, L., A. Sklar, C., Li, S., Liu, Q., Gimpel, N., Yasui, Y., A. Whitton, J., Stovall, M., L. Robison, L., C. Oeffinger, K. 2009. Diabetes Mellitus in Long-term Survivors of Childhood Cancer. Archives of Internal Medicine, 169: 1381&amp;rdquo;. &lt;a href="https://publons.com/review/227452/"&gt;Publons review 227452&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Francisco H C Felix. (2009). Pre-publication review of &amp;ldquo;L. Cox, C., M. Hudson, M., Mertens, A., Oeffinger, K., Whitton, J., Montgomery, M., L. Robison, L. 2009. Medical Screening Participation in the Childhood Cancer Survivor Study. Archives of Internal Medicine, 169: 454&amp;rdquo;. &lt;a href="https://publons.com/review/227467/"&gt;Publons review 227467&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cite as: Francisco H C Felix. (2016). Alternative types of academic publications. Zenodo. 10.5281/zenodo.594582&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="references"&gt;References:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Larivière V, Haustein S, Mongeon P. The Oligopoly of Academic Publishers in
the Digital Era. PLoS One. 2015;10(6):e0127502. doi:
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0127502"&gt;10.1371/journal.pone.0127502&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kieńć, Witold. Authors from the periphery countries choose open access more often. Learned Publishing 2017;30.2: 125-131.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guédon, J-C (2007). Open access and the divide between ‘mainstream’ and ‘peripheral’ science, in Ferreira, S, Mara SP &amp;amp; Targino, M das G (eds.), Como gerir e qualificar revistas científicas, &lt;a href="http://eprints.rclis.org/10778/"&gt;http://eprints.rclis.org/10778/&lt;/a&gt;, accessed in 09/21/2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meriläinen, Susan, et al. &amp;ldquo;Hegemonic academic practices: experiences of publishing from the periphery.&amp;rdquo; Organization 2008; 15.4: 584-597.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cardoso, RV &amp;amp; Meijers, EJ. Contrasts between first-tierand second-tier cities in Europe: a functional perspective, European Planning Studies, 2016; 24:5,996-1015, DOI: &lt;a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/284730738_Contrasts_between_First-tier_and_Second-tier_Cities_in_Europe_a_functional_perspective"&gt;10.1080/09654313.2015.112070&lt;/a&gt; [accessed Sep 21, 2017].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Loureiro, Luiz Victor Maia, Callegaro Filho, Donato, Rocha, Altieres de Arruda, Prado, Bernard Lobato, Mutão, Taciana Sousa, Donnarumma, Carlos del Cistia, &amp;amp; Giglio, Auro del. Existe viés de publicação para artigos brasileiros sobre câncer?. Einstein (São Paulo), 2013; 11(1), 15-22. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1590/S1679-45082013000100005"&gt;https://dx.doi.org/10.1590/S1679-45082013000100005&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dickersin, K.; Chan, S.; Chalmers, T. C.; et al. &amp;ldquo;Publication bias and clinical trials&amp;rdquo;. Controlled Clinical Trials 1987; 8 (4): 343–353. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0197-2456(87)90155-3"&gt;https://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0197-2456(87)90155-3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lee, K. &amp;amp; Bero, L. Increasing accountability. What authors, editors and reviewers should do to improve peer review. Nature 2006 &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature05007"&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/nature05007&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ware, M., &amp;amp; Mabe, M. (2015). The STM Report. &lt;a href="http://www.stm-assoc.org/2015_02_20_STM_Report_2015.pdf"&gt;http://www.stm-assoc.org/2015_02_20_STM_Report_2015.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bohannon, John. &amp;ldquo;Who&amp;rsquo;s Afraid of Peer Review?&amp;rdquo;. Science 2013; 342 (6154): 60–65. &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.342.6154.60"&gt;https://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.342.6154.60&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arns, M. Open access is tiring out peer reviewers. Nature 2014; 515, 467 &lt;a href="https://doi.org/doi:10.1038/515467a"&gt;doi:10.1038/515467a&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Van Noorden, R. Open access: The true cost of science publishing. Nature 2013; 495, 426–429 &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.1038/495426a"&gt;doi:10.1038/495426a&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Davis, P. PeerJ Membership Model and The Paradox Of The Loyal Customer. &lt;a href="https://scholarlykitchen.sspnet.org/2017/05/08/peerj-membership-model-paradox-loyal-customer/"&gt;The Scholarly Kitchen&lt;/a&gt;, accessed in 21/09/2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pinheiro, LVR. Do acesso livre à ciência aberta: conceitos e implicações na comunicação científica. RECIIS – Rev. Eletron. de Comun. Inf. Inov. Saúde. 2014; 8(2): 153-165 &lt;a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.3395/reciis.v8i2.946.pt"&gt;doi:10.3395/reciis.v8i2.946.pt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="pelican"></category><category term="gitlab"></category><category term="open access"></category><category term="green way"></category></entry></feed>